<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The way to heauen In a sermon deliuered at Saint Maries Spittle on Wednesday in Easter weeke the 27. of March. 1611. By Samuel Gardiner, Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Gardiner, Samuel, b. 1563 or 4.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115875</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851092</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851092</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16347</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01456)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16347)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1099:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The way to heauen In a sermon deliuered at Saint Maries Spittle on Wednesday in Easter weeke the 27. of March. 1611. By Samuel Gardiner, Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Gardiner, Samuel, b. 1563 or 4.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[86] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By W. W[hite] for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F⁴ (-F4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Some pages marked and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16347:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16347:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE WAY TO HEAVEN.</p>
            <p>IN A Sermon deliuered at Saint <hi>Maries</hi> Spittle on Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday in Eaſter weeke the 27. of March. 1611.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SAMVEL GARDINER,</hi> Doctor of Diuinitie.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>W. W.</hi> for THOMAS MAN. 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16347:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE, THE VERTV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lady, <hi>JANE</hi> Lady <hi>BARKLEY,</hi> wife to HENRY, Lord BARKLEY.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SAMVEL GARDINER</hi> Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crateth this his Sermon in teſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his dutifull affections.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16347:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 8.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The ſame Spirit beareth witneſse with our Spirit, that we are the children of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing lately handled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, the doctrine of the certaintie of our Election; I hold it fitte now, to open the veine of theſe two Queſtions, naturally incident vnto the former Argument. 1. Whether a man may know his particular Election. 2. How it may be knowne. This Scripture that teacheth how it may be knowne, plainely inſinuateth that it may be knowne. How it may be knowne, it is heere told vs: the mouth of two witneſſes the beſt that is in Heauen; <hi>The Spirit of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>which ſearcheth all thinges, yea the deepe thinges of God.</hi> 2. The beſt that is in Earth, <hi>The Spirit of man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> 
               <hi>that onely knoweth the thinges of man within him,</hi> reuealing it vnto vs.</p>
            <p>By theſe degrees, as by the Staues of <hi>Iacobs</hi> Ladder, we aſcend vp to this ſacred coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile of his Sanctuarie. <hi>Our owne Spirit,</hi> is
<pb facs="tcp:16347:3"/> our Heart and Conſcience, ſanctified in the ſprinkling of the Blood of Chriſt. <hi>The Spirit of God,</hi> is ioyned by God vnto it, to helpe our infirmities. <hi>Our Spirit</hi> teſtifieth moral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of our Adoption, by ſanctification, and the fruites thereof. <hi>The Spirit of God</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth an other way; that is, by the abſolute certaintie of Fayth, declaring and applying the Promiſes of God.</p>
            <p>Foure maner of wayes, may one be ſaid to be the Child of God. 1. By naturall or eſſentiall Generation: in this ſenſe, Chriſt Ieſus is the onely Sonne of God, begotten of the ſubſtaunce of his Father before all worldes. 2. By the grace of Hypoſtaticall vnion with the naturall Sonne of God: thus Chriſt as man, is the Sonne of God, and the borne Sonne of God. 3. By grace of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as they that are elected and put apart to this, to be Sonnes, and ſo ioynt heyres with Chriſt in his Kingdome; in this meaning, Chriſt is ſayd to haue died,<note place="margin">Iohn. 11.52.</note> 
               <hi>To gather togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one, the children of God, that were ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:</hi> that is, the Elect, not as yet regenerated. 4. By grace of Regeneration; according to the ſaying of Chriſt to <hi>Nicodemus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>Except a man be borne againe of the Spirit, hee can not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the kingdome of God.</hi> Heere to be the Child of God, is to be Predeſtinated into the Adoption of his Children,<note place="margin">Epheſ 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath Predeſtinated vs to be adopted through Jeſus
<pb facs="tcp:16347:3"/> Chriſt in himſelfe.</hi> Next, to be made actually, &amp; indeed the Child of God through Fayth; <hi>As many as receiued him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>to them he gaue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue to be the Sonnes of God; euen to them that beleeue in his name.</hi> Finally, by the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to be regenerated into the child of God, and to put on the nature of the Sonne of God Chriſt Ieſus, or to put on Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe, according to the Apoſtles phraſe of ſpeach; <hi>Put on the new man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.24.</note> 
               <hi>which after God is created vnto righteouſneſse and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Now the Priuiledges are royall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed by God to thoſe whom he hath thus Adopted his Children. They are the Lords Heyres apparant, it is the conſequent the Apoſtle maketh; 1. <hi>If we be Children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> 
               <hi>we be alſo Heyres, euen the Heyres of God.</hi> 2. Fellow-heyres with Chriſt, ſo are they ſurnamed in the ſame place: <hi>Heyres annexed with Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> 3. Yea Kinges at all degrees; ſo the ſpirit ſpeaketh euidently:<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>And made vs Kinges and Prieſtes, euen to God his Father.</hi> 4. All their Afflictions, Wantes, Offences, are but probations, and fatherly Corrections layde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them for their good; as it is written, <hi>We know that all thinges worke togeather for the beſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> 
               <hi>vnto them that love God.</hi> 5. They haue a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding &amp; imperial power ouer all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; yet ſo, as in this life they haue but, <hi>Jus adrem,</hi> Right to the thing. In the fift that is to come, they ſhall haue, <hi>Jus in re,</hi> Right
<pb facs="tcp:16347:4"/> and ful ſtate in the verie thing it ſelfe; world, life, death, thinges preſent, thinges to come, euen all are yours:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>b. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Thou madeſt him litle inferiour to the Angels, thou crowneſt him with Glory and Honour, and hast ſet him aboue the workes of thine handes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſ. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt put all things in ſubiection vnder his feete.</hi> 6. Laſtly, the very Angels are Officers at hand to giue attendaunce vnto them, and to watch ouer their good:<note place="margin">Ieb. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>Are they not all miniſtring Spirites, ſent foorth to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter for their ſakes which ſhall be heyres of ſaluation?</hi> Whereto anſwereth this part of Pſalmodie;<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.7.</note> 
               <hi>The Angell of the Lord pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth round about them that feare him, and deliuereth them.</hi> Hereupon let me ſpeake in the language of <hi>Dauid; Seemeth it a ſmall thing that I be Sonne in law to a King, ſithence I am poore and of no reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> So ſeemeth it a ſmall thing to vs, to be adopted into the Children of God, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wormes,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.1.</note> and no Men: <hi>Behold what loue the Father hath giuen vs, that wee ſhould be called the Sonnes of God.</hi> It was a part of high honour done to our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.16.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham, Izaac, Iacob,</hi> that <hi>God was not aſhamed to be called their God:</hi> No leſſe honour is performed to vs, that
<pb facs="tcp:16347:4"/> hee is our God, and wee his people: hee our Father, and wee his Children. Now the Spirit of God, while it inwardly wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth to our Spirit, that is, to our Mindes, by illuminating them by the Sun-beames of his Grace that wee are the Children of God; hee doth plainely and openly reueale to vs, that we were from all eternitie, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opted into his Son-ſhip. For they are not by Fayth the Children of God, neither are they regenerated into the Children of God, or haue put on Chriſt, who haue not firſt been Predeſtinated vnto this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>option.</p>
            <p>And heere now come our firſt Queſtion in place, to be ventilated and decided; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a man may know his particuler Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Papiſtes ſay no, without ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſpeciall reuelation. A verie erroneous and abſurd aſſertion, eaſily checked by Scriptures and Reaſons.</p>
            <p>By Scriptures, as by the words of Chriſt to his Diſciples,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.20.</note> 
               <hi>Reioyce that your Names are written in Heauen:</hi> But, <hi>Ignot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nulla cupido,</hi> no man reioyceth in a thing either vnknowne, or vncertaine vnto him. By this Precept of <hi>Peter, Giue diligence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.10.</note> to make your election ſure. Now herein what would all our diligence doe good, if it could not be made ſure? Laſtly, in this perſwaſion of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians: Prooue your ſelues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.5.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:16347:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:16347:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:16347:6"/> 
               <hi>whether yee be in the fayth or not? Know yee not your owne ſelus, how that Joſues Chriſt is in you, except ye be reprobates?</hi> Where it is aſſumed as a matter confeſſed, that a man may know his Fayth, and ſo his Election; Fayth being the infallible marke of our Election.</p>
            <p>By Reaſons wee confront them in the cauſe, thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That which a man is bound certainely to beleeue, he may certainely know, and that without notice of ſpeciall Reuelation: But euery faythfull man ſtandeth bound to beleeue that he is elected, it being the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue precept of God, that wee beleeue in Chriſt:<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.23.</note> 
               <hi>This is his commaundement, that wee beleeue in the Name of his ſonne Ieſus Christ.</hi> To beleeue in Chriſt, being not onely to beleeue that we are Adopted, Iuſtified, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by him; but alſo eternally to be Elected in him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Againe we diſpute thus. That which is conſigned and ſealed vnto vs by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, of that we may be ſure; for then are wee ſure of our Leaſes and Grauntes, when they are ſealed vnto vs. But our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>option, and ſo by ſequell our Election, is ſealed vnto vs by the Spirit of God. This Scriptures conceale not, but reueale vnto vs,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 2.12.</note> where they ſay: <hi>Wee haue receiued not the Spirit of the world, but the Spirit which is of God, that we might know the thinges that are giuen to
<pb facs="tcp:16347:6"/> vs of God.</hi> As in an other place thus:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>Jn whom alſo ye haue truſted, after that yee heard the word of trueth, euen the Goſpell of your ſaluation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> alſo after that yee beleeued, yee were ſealed with the holy Spirit of Promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If our Aduerſaries hereto ſhall obiect, that this obſignation of our Adoption is morally by our works, to beare vs in hand, that this our knowledge of our Adoption, is but coniecturall and probable; wee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwere, that the holy Spirit ſealeth our Adoption, by begetting in vs, a ſpeciall confidence. For when as we heare the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God, and withall ruminate and meditate vpon them, in commeth the holy Ghoſt in the nicke, inclining the Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding &amp; the Will, to imbrace them; and then draweth them on to giue conſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and to reſt contented in them: Whence ariſeth that ſpeciall aſſurance, that we are Gods adopted Children, and that wee ſtand in his fauour.</p>
            <p>If further it ſhall be obiected, that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike-fayth chargeth none, to giue Fayth to that, which God neither by written or vnwritten Word, or otherwiſe by Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hath intimated vnto vs: and how that by none of theſe wayes, it hath been ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted that this man <hi>Peter,</hi> or that man <hi>Cornelias,</hi> is Predeſtinated by God: and therefore that no man is conſtrained par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
<pb facs="tcp:16347:7"/> to beleeue, this or that man to be ſaued: let them be thus anſwered, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit this particular propoſition, <hi>J am Elected,</hi> be not ſo broadly ſet downe in the Bible, yet incluſiuely as <hi>Species in ſico genere,</hi> as Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians ſpeake, is it there contained. So as by naturall collectiue inference, it is ſet downe in the word by diſputing in this manner:<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.35.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoeuer truely beleeue, are elected: But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aruely doe beleeue, therefore J am elected.</hi> The Propoſition or firſt part of this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is the verie Scripture: the Aſſumption or ſecond part, commeth from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the beleeuing perſon. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion naturally iſſueth from them both.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Our next Argument, ſhalbe thus for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. The Fayth of the Elect, or otherwiſe, that which we call, A ſauing Fayth, is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and particuler perſwaſion of forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes, and of eternall life. That Fayth is this reſolute perſwaſion; and that this Reſolution is of the nature of Fayth. Scriptures doe conclude: as where Chriſt ſayth to <hi>Peter;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 14.31.</note> 
               <hi>O thou of litle Fayth, wherefore did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>est thou doubt?</hi> As where he ſayth to his Diſciples;<note place="margin">Math. 21.21.</note> 
               <hi>If yee haue Fayth, and doubt not.</hi> As where Saint <hi>James</hi> moniſheth thus: <hi>Let him aske in Fayth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>and wauer not.</hi> The Fayth that was ſo much commended in <hi>Abraham; He doubted not of the Promiſe of God through vnbeliefe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.20.</note> 
               <hi>but was strengthned in the Fayth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16347:7"/>
            <p>In the ſecond place, that Fayth is a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler perſwaſion, applying thinges belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, it is thus prooued. The propertie of Fayth is to receiue the Promiſe; ſo S. <hi>Paul, That yee might receiue the Promiſe of the Spirit through Fayth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.14.</note> and the thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, which is Chriſt with his ſpirit: of which ſayth our Sauiour, <hi>As many as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>to them he gaue prerogatiue to be the Sonnes of God, euen to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in his Name.</hi> It is this that giueth vs courage and confidence; theſe two beeing the worthy effectes of our Fayth, as <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth, ſaying:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>By Chriſt we haue bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; entraunce with confidence by Fayth in him.</hi> Boldneſſe is, when a ſinner dare preſſe into the preſence of God, and not be diſmaide with the menaces of the Law, or the vnderſtanding of his owne vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor with the manifold tryalles of the Diuell: and it is more then certaintie of Gods fauour; which a generall Fayth can not breed, as <hi>Papistes</hi> would haue it. This generall Fayth, without doubt, beeing in <hi>Cain, Saul, Achitophel, Iudas,</hi> and ſuch like; yea, in <hi>Sathan</hi> himſelfe, who not-withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding deſpaired, and ſome of them deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly did fordoe themſelues; and the Diuell for all his fayth, quiuereth as a Leafe toſſed with the wind, in the preſence of God.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb facs="tcp:16347:8"/>4. Laſtly, I oppoſe againſt them th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> multiplicitie of inſtances as very pregnan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proofes of the cauſe congeſted by S. <hi>Iohn</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his firſt Epiſtle, whoſe intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the whole Letter is to ſhew, how a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may ordinarily and plenarily know, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hee is in Gods loue, and ſo in the ſtate o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eternall life. The places are very ſtrong on our ſide, and they are theſe: <hi>Hereby we are ſure that we know him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 23.</note> 
               <hi>if we keepe his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 5.</note> 
               <hi>If we keepe his word, hereby we know that we are in him. In this are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> children of God knowne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>and the children of the Diuell. Thereby we know that we are of the trueth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 19.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhall before him aſſure our heartes. Hereby we know that we dwel in him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>and he in vs, becauſe he hath giuen vs of his ſpirit. Theſe thinges haue I writen vnto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>that beleeue in the name of the ſonne of God, that yee may know that y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> haue eternall life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now our Aduerſaries thus ſlubber vp an anſwere to theſe Teſtimonies. 1. That none of them doe neceſſarily imply any ſuch certaintie of Diuine knowledge, in aſmuch as thoſe thinges which we learne by coniectures, we may be ſayd to know. This is but an hungrie Anſwere, by their leaue, and a very miſerable ſhift; which
<pb facs="tcp:16347:8"/> with what facilitie we liſt, we diſſolue and doe away. For thus S. <hi>Iohn</hi> directly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth vs the drift of his Epiſtle:<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe thinges write we vnto you, that your ioy may be full.</hi> But it muſt needes be an vncertaine ioy, which a doubtfull and coniecturall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge doth beget. Againe, this knowledge naturally bringeth foorth ſecuritie &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence; as where the ſame Apoſtle ſayth,<note place="margin">Cap. 3.19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Wee know that wee are in the trueth, and ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him aſſure our heartes: and we haue boldneſſe towardes God:</hi> And therefore it can not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, but include an abſolute aſſurance. Finally, that hee might apparantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that this knowledge is a knowledge of diuine Fayth, are altogeather as infallible as it may bee; he commeth in with this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in the next Chapter;<note place="margin">Cap. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>We haue knowne and beleeued the loue that God hath in vs.</hi> Now where as our Aduerſaries come in with this ſurioynder, that theſe tearmes are generall, nothing concerning any one in particuler: it is vntrue that they ſay: For where as <hi>John</hi> ſpeaketh in the plurall number, <hi>Wee haue knowne,</hi> he ſpeaketh of himſelfe, and in himſelfe of the reſidue of the Church, wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and infolded in the ſame condition. Now hee himſelfe knew certainely that he ſhould be ſaued: For Chriſt, not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he left the World, filled their heartes with ioy and gladneſſe, partly by repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:16347:9"/> and renewing the Promiſe of Etern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> life, and of the perpetuall preſence of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Spirit; and partly by praying to his Fathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for them, for their finall preſeruation: ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they might irrefragably conclude their aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſured ſaluation, both for the preſent, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the life to come.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing concluded the affirmati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of this Queſtion, let vs now conſider wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Aduerſaries can ſay for the Negatiue and Deſtructiue part thereof.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, they tell vs of <hi>Job,</hi> who for a his integritie, was without this certaint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſecuritie of Grace, as where he thus be wrayeth it;<note place="margin">Iob. 9.21.</note> 
               <hi>Though I were perfect, yet my ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſh uld not know it;</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 28.</note> 
               <hi>I am afraide of all my works</hi> I anſwere by <hi>Hierome,</hi> that heere hee ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth by way of compariſon with God an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelfe, eſpecially when hee entreth int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> iudgement with the creature, in which caſe he diſclaymeth his owne righteouſneſſe, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not being able to abide the tryall; ſo that that this ſpeach, <hi>My ſoule ſhould not know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> is as much as if he ſhould haue ſayd, I wil not acknowledge or ſtand vpon my righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſneſſe: which is no leſſe then the very Angels can ſay which are alreadie in Hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, and are heerein aforehand with him Againe, the wordes according to the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, are commonly tranſlated, and to be read thus; <hi>Am I perfect? I know not my ſouls,
<pb facs="tcp:16347:9"/> I abhorre my life:</hi> That is, if I take my ſelfe to bee perfect, I haue no regard of mine owne Soule: Againe thus, I am perfect in reſpect of you, &amp; I know not my ſoule, &amp; I abhorre thy life, namely in reſpect of mine owne righteousneſſe: The wordes of the 28. verſe are thus to be deliuered: <hi>I fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e all my ſorrowes,</hi> and not all my workes, as flatte againſt the <hi>Hebrew</hi> text, and an expoſition which the Popiſh Tranſlators doe forſake.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next they pleading againſt vs,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.1.2.</note> from the wordes of the Preacher, thus: <hi>Man knovves not vvhether he be vvorthie of Loue, or Hatred: For all thinges are kept vncertaine, till the time to come.</hi> But it will not ſerue their turne, for the tranſlation is not right; for the wordes in the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> and <hi>Septuagint,</hi> ſtand thus: <hi>No man knoweth loue or hatred; all things are before them.</hi> The latter wordes, <hi>All things are kept vncertaine, till the time to come,</hi> come in by intruſion: <hi>Hierome</hi> taketh no notice of them.</p>
            <p>Againe, the holy Ghoſt doth not ſimply denie the knowledge of Gods loue, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, as though no man could be aſſured thereof in this life. For to conſture the wordes ſo, the reaſon of the holy Ghoſt muſt be faſhioned in this manner: If Loue or Hatred were to be knowne, then it muſt be knowne by the eternall bleſsings of God: but it cannot be ſo knowne, in aſmuch
<pb facs="tcp:16347:10"/> as all thinges come alike to all; therefore Loue and Hatred can not be knowne Now ſo the Propoſition is not true: For there be other meanes beſide the outward benefites of God; wherefore the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the wordes is that Loue or Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred are not to be conſidered of, or deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by Gods outward fauours. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. ſerm. de octau. paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha.</note> ſpeaketh of this Text thus, that no man knowes Loue or Hatred, namely of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; yet that God giues moſt certaine and aſſured teſtimonies thereof to men vpon earth:<note place="margin">Serm. 5. de dedic.</note> Theſe be his owne wordes; <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knowes whether he be worthy loue or hatred. Who knowes the minde of the Lord? Heere, both Fayth and trueth muſt needes helpe vs; that, that which is hidden in the heart of the Father, may be reuealed vnto vs by the Spirit: and his Spirit giuing teſtimonie, perſwades our Spirit, that we are the Sonnes of God; and this perſwaſion is cauſed by his Calling and Iuſtifying vs freely by Fayth. Hieromes</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. in hunc locum.</note> wordes on this place, (though commonly abuſed to a contrarie ſenſe,) are theſe, That men can not know Loue or Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred by the preſent afflictions which they ſuffer, becauſe they know not whether they ſuffer them for probation, or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:16347:10"/>3. Thirdly,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.3.4.</note> they preſſe vs with theſe wordes of the Apoſtle, <hi>I iudge not my ſelfe, I know nothing by my ſelfe:</hi> Where <hi>Paul</hi> not priuie to his owne eſtate, refuſeth to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce doome of his owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But it is manifeſt by the wordes of that Epiſtle, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh nothing of his owne perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or of eſtate before God; but onely of the function of his Miniſtrie, and the eminencie thereof againſt certaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prauers of that calling amongſt the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> as <hi>Theodoret, Aquina,</hi> and <hi>Lyra,</hi> doe auerre in their Scholies vpon this text. So that where he ſaith <hi>J Iudge not my ſelfe,</hi> it is as if he ſhould haue ſayd, I aſſume not to my ſelfe to ſtand in compariſon of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of my Miniſtrie, &amp; dignitie of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip in the ſight of God, aboue this man or that, that is in the Miniſtrie; the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the Lordes, and I leaue it to him to whom it belongeth. So that heere he onely refuſeth to value and prize the worthineſſe of his Office, though in other caſes, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no bones to giue Iudgement of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as when he ſayd,<note place="margin">2. Tim 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8</note> 
               <hi>I haue fought a good fight, J haue kept the fayth; hencefoorth is layde vp for mee the crowne of righteouſneſse, which the Lord the righteous Iudge ſhall giue mee.</hi> And <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> on this place ſayth, that <hi>Paul</hi> did not denie to iudge himſelfe ſimply, but onely to this purpoſe, to bridle others, and
<pb facs="tcp:16347:11"/> to teach them modeſtie. And where <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>I know nothing by my ſelfe;</hi> his ſaying is not generall, but it is to haue reſtraint to his defectes, and offences, in the courſe of his Miniſterie: for he was priuie to himſelfe, <hi>That in ſimplicitie and godly pureneſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>he had his conuerſation in the worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> And hee knew this by himſelfe,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.38.</note> 
               <hi>That nothing could ſeauer him from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oue of God in Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth Obiection is thus laide in againſt vs. There can be no Iuſtification, where there is not Fayth and Repentance: But no man can be certaine by the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Fayth of his vnfained Repentance of his ſinnes paſt, and of ſuch a Fayth as God requireth of vs, in aſmuch as the worde performes no teſtimonie of our particuler Fayth and Repentance: therefore no man can be certaine by the certaintie of Fayth, that his ſinnes are forgiuen him.</p>
            <p>Our Anſwere is this; that a man by his Fayth, ſhould be certaine of his Fayth and Repentance; there is no ſuch neceſsitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the obiect of Fayth is not of thinges preſent, but of thinges to come; whereas Fayth and Repentance are truely preſent in all that truely beleeue and repent; it will ſuffice if any man any way be vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly certaine that he hath them.</p>
            <p>And albeit ſome men fondly feed vpon their owne Fancie, as vpon a Reſtoratiue,
<pb facs="tcp:16347:11"/> that they haue Fayth, and haue it not; as they that dreame that they are great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp; when they are out of their dreame, finde the contrarie: yet the true beleeuer, knoweth aſwell that hee beleeueth, as hee that vnderſtandeth, knoweth hee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth; and as hee that beleeueth a man on his word, knoweth hee beleeueth him; and as hee that holdeth Monie in his hand, knoweth that hee holdeth it. Wherefore <hi>Paul</hi> calleth on the <hi>Corintians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.5.</note> to prooue whether they haue Fayth or no, to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate that it is a poynt to be prooued, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned of vs: And hee profeſſeth this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning skill in himſelfe, where hee ſayth, <hi>J know whom J haue beleeued.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.12.</note> And S. <hi>Iohn</hi> maketh it as cleare as the Sunne,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.24.</note> 
               <hi>By th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s wee know that hee dwelles in vs, by the ſpirit which he hath giuen vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas they vrge vs further here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that albeit we may know that we haue this Fayth, yet we can not know whether it be of ſufficiencie or no, for our ſecuritie in this cauſe.</p>
            <p>We anſwere, that true Fayth not blinded with hypocriſie, in the mediocritie and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection thereof, ſufficeth to aſſure vs of our particuler Election, as the leaſt meaſure of <hi>Manna</hi> fedde them in the Deſart,<note place="margin">Exod. 6.</note> as well as they that came in with <hi>Cornu copta,</hi> and had made greater prouiſion: As a Palſie
<pb facs="tcp:16347:12"/> ſhaking Hand could receiue the benefite of an Almes, as well as the ſtrongeſt Arme and ſoundeſt Hand of all: As the Fleſh, that is the weakeſt part of man, hath as much vinacitie in it, as the very ſtones that are of ſuch ſolide and firme compoſition: The ſinceritie of our Fayth beeing of more worth with God, then the perfection of it. The Will with God, is the meaſure of the action; &amp; the Deſire of any Grace in God; is the very Grace it ſelfe. He that hath but a Will to ſerue God, hath the Spirit of God; and hee that hath the Spirit of God, is in Chriſt: and hee that is in Chriſt, ſhall neuer ſee damnation. God will approoue his owne workes which he hath wrought in thee, and will not reiect thee for thy worke.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A fift Obiection throwne vpon vs, hath deduction from ſuch Scripture autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, as commende <hi>Feare</hi> vnto vs; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie qualitie (as it ſhould ſeeme to this godly ſecuritie of Conſcience) that this Doctrine of the Knowledge of our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer Election ſeemeth to implie: as where <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. 28.14.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſsed is the man that Feareth alway.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ul. 2.12.</note> As where <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>Worke your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation with Feare and trembling.</hi> As where the ſame Apoſtle ſayth,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.20.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſtandeſt by Fayth, be not high minded, but Feare.</hi> As where the royall Prophet in the Ode,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.11.</note> ſayth, <hi>Serue the Lord in Feare, and reioyce in trembling.</hi> Vpon
<pb facs="tcp:16347:12"/> which places, <hi>Stapleton</hi> croweth as a Cocke on the dunghill, out of the aduantage that he preſumeth he hath againſt our Doctrine, which he ſayth, giue the foyle to our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeite Fayth, of our perſwaſion of Gods Loue not poſsibly to be loſt; and to the opinion we hold of the indeleble Fayth of the Elect: and to all our Diuinitie of the certaintie of Grace and Saluation. His Sophiſtication and fallacie, is thus framed: Where there yet remaineth to the beleeuer, and to him that ſtandeth in the Fayth, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of feare, there this conceiued Beliefe of ours, this Fayth inexpungible, this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous aſſurance; can not haue a place His reaſon is; becauſe nothing is more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe to Securitie, then Feare; nothing more deſtroyeth this our certaintie of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, then this our facilitie of poſsibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of falling from Grace: neither may that be deemed indeleble, that is in ſuch danger and hazard to be loſt. But the Apoſtle (ſayth he) ſtriketh with feare, yea ſuch as beleeue, and ſtand in the ſayth; therefore in this ſecuritie of ours, there is an abſolute nullitie.</p>
            <p>I cannot greatly blame him for his dowtie diſpute, to keepe vs ſtill in ſuſpenſe of our ſaluation; for the Doctor knoweth well, that all their queſtuous occupation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they liue, is in the life of this their lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
<pb facs="tcp:16347:13"/> doctrine, and how that if this our diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie ſhould ſtand, they might burne their Bookes, as the Bookes of curious artes were ſerued, ſpoken of by <hi>Luke</hi> in the Actes of the Apoſtles: for the whole maſſe and waight of all their building, their Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Maſſe, Indulgences, Satisfactions, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, and the whole Papacie, leaneth vpon this baſe, of baſe minded Doctrine, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of ſaluation; without which doubt, out of doubt all would come tumbling downe with a witneſſe, at the ſound of this our Preaching, as the Walles of <hi>Hiericho</hi> ſometimes did at the noyſe of the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets of Rammes hornes.</p>
            <p>But I anſwere <hi>Stap e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> in his Argument, that the Aſſumption of his Sillogiſme, is faultie two wayes. 1. Firſt, for that the Apoſtle doth not put feare into the heartes of the faythfull ſtanding in the Fayth; but only ſuch as make detraction fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Faith; ſuch as our Hipocrites, and ſeruers of the times: ſuch as neuer indeed beeing in the Fayth, can not tarrie or ſtand in the Fayth. Secondly, he doth not affright the faithfull ſtanders in the Fayth, with the terrour of their fall, but onely moniſheth them to that feare which conſiſteth in modeſtie and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his Bookes of <hi>Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. lib. 3. cap. 12. de Iuſtificat.</note> to eſtabliſh this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſters, and to ouerthrow our poſition of
<pb facs="tcp:16347:13"/> the certaine knowledge of our Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vſeth the ſelfe-ſame argument, more briefly framed, thus: <hi>Where feare is, there is no aſsurance: but we are all willed to feare, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo e there is no aſſurance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Propoſition is true vnderſtood of the ſeruile feare, vnable to ſtand with this aſſurance: for this feare is in the Diuels, who beleeue and tremble: But as it hath reference to the filiall feare, which is a feare of God, of modeſtie, of humilitie, it is erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous &amp; falſe: for it is in the nature of this feare, not to quench, but to kindle Fayth, to conſerue, and to increaſe it. Againe, there is, <hi>Fallacia non cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae,</hi> in the Minor: For we are commaunded to feare not by doubting of Grace, but by auoyding of ſinne, pride, and diſpleaſure of God. Thirdly, thoſe threates and terrours, are indefinite, pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly reſpecting Hipocrites lurking in the Church, who beleeue, and ſtand by that Fayth onely, <hi>Quae creatur,</hi> which is belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the profeſsion of the doctrine: but they doe not beleeue, &amp; ſtand in the Fayth, <hi>Qua crea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur,</hi> in the which it is beleeued, that is, in the aſſuraunce of the heart: Now of ſuch onely is the Minor to be taken, and ſo wee giue them the whole argum nt of ſuch as are truely faythfull, it is falſe</p>
            <p>The Conſequent rayſed out of this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, VVorke your ſituation
<pb facs="tcp:16347:14"/> with feare and trembling:</hi> Therefore the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full may feare their fall. Beeing applyed to the feare that is cautelous and carefull, is not to be denied: For the faythfull muſt feare; that is, take heed they fall not, and foreſee that they plunge not themſelues through ſecuritie, into vtter perdition. This feare, Fayth it ſelfe naturally doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get; and this Care, is the Tribute that is due vnto it. But as it conſidereth the feare of doubt, and diſtruſt of Gods grace, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent is vntrue; for the Apoſtle by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting men to ſuch feare, ſhould derogate from the Promiſes of God, and to giue the lye vnto him. Therefore both <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pleton</hi> doe but wrangle with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles argument. This feare of working of our ſaluation, is not in reſpect of Gods mercie forgiuing our ſinnes, but in reſpect of vs and our nature; which is euer apt to turne aſide from God.</p>
            <p>There is a threefold feare. 1. Of Nature. 2. Grace. 3. Diſtruſt. 1. That of Nature is that, whereby the nature of man is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with that, which any way ſtriueth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; and therefore auoydeth it 2. Feare of Grace, is that mother Grace of all others, which <hi>Salomon</hi> calleth, <hi>The beginning of Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;</hi> and it is a kind of awe or reuerence vnto God, as conſidering how wee are in the preſence of God, in all thinges wee doe.
<pb facs="tcp:16347:14"/> 3. Feare of Diſtruſt, is that melancholie and cruell feare that ſtabbeth the heart with the ſword of Gods Iudgements, in the ſenſe and ſight men haue of their ſinnes, without hope of recouerie. The firſt of theſe three, was good by Creation;<note place="margin">Marc. 14.</note> and therefore our Sauiour was not free of this, for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of him; <hi>Hee began to feare.</hi> The third is naught; called a Seruile feare. The ſecond is that which is ſo often commended and commaunded vnto vs in theſe, and ſuch like authorities of Scripture; whoſe nature is onely to make vs more warie and heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of our ſelues, that wee runne not into ſinne, while we conſider our owne Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Gods eternall Iudgementes: And this kind of feare, as well as the firſt, agree well enough with the certaintie of Fayth, and can ſtand togeather. In one and the ſame reſpect, they will not combine; but in ſome diuerſitie of Nature and Reaſon, they goe hand in hand togeather. The Saintes of God on the one ſide, are ſmitten with feare, while they recount their ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and ſo fearefull falles: and withall, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how the mouth of the Law condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſinne, the hand of God ſtriketh it; how he ſpared not Angels, Kingdomes, Cities; nay not his owne Sonne, being in the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of ſinfull fleſh: On the other ſide, while they regard the Promiſes of God,
<pb facs="tcp:16347:15"/> and called to minde the tender mercies of God which haue been euer of old, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue comfort, and expell all feare; and they ſet ſure foote in the Sanctuarie of the Lord. Diuerſe cauſes, breed diuerſe effectes in the mindes of men. A man that is in the toppe of an exceeding high Tower, while his minde is intent vnto nothing elſe, but how he may be in danger to fall and ſo wholly looketh downeward, he cannot but feare: but while hee conſidereth that the place where he ſtandeth hath ſuch Battlementes about, and that hee is ſo mured in with a Wall that hee can not fall, hee eaſily doth ridde himſelfe of this feare.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The ſixt Obiection is thus mooued. To beleeue that our ſinnes are forgiuen vs, is no Article of our Beliefe; and therefore wee haue nothing to doe to beleeue it.</p>
            <p>I anſwere them, it is; vnder theſe words, <hi>I beleeue the forgiueneſs of ſinnes.</hi> I conclude it thus. The Diuell beleeueth generally, and ingroſſe that God pardoneth the Church their ſinnes: but we are to wade further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Fayth then the Diuell, and apply this remiſsion of ſinnes, euerie one of vs particulerly to our owne ſoules. If the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes will not haue their Catholicke ſayth to be better then the Diuels, let them for all vs, keepe their Fayth to them ſelues.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The ſeuenth Obiection ſtandeth thus:
<pb facs="tcp:16347:15"/> In reſpect of Gods Mercie, wee muſt hope for Saluation; but in reſpect of our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe, wee muſt doubt the Promiſe of the Remiſsion of our ſinnes, not being independant, but conditionall thereafter according as our workes be.</p>
            <p>Wee anſwere firſt; Wee may not at all lawfully doubt of Gods Mercie, becauſe doubtfulneſſe is not of the nature of Fayth, but rather a naturall corruption. 2. If wee conſider our owne vnworthineſſe, it is out of all doubt we muſt be out of all hope, and deſpaire of our ſaluation. S. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>They which are of the workes of the Law, are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the curſe:</hi> And ſo he ſpeaketh in his owne caſe, of his owne workes of grace,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>Jn this I am not iuſtified.</hi> So <hi>Dauid</hi> being out of all doubt of his owne deſerued damnation, ſayth ingeniouſly thus: <hi>Enter not into Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with thy ſeruant O Lord, for no fleſh ſhall be iuſtified in thy ſight.</hi> Alſo, the regard of our owne vnworthineſſe, is no preiudice to the reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods mercie in Chriſt. For true Fayth maketh an entrance vnto God with boldneſſe, euen for thoſe perſons that are vnworthy in themſelues. The <hi>Centurion</hi> that confeſſed himſelfe vnworthy vnder whoſe rooſe Chriſt might enter;<note place="margin">Math. 8.8.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Luc. 15.1</note> yet is a ſuppliant to Chriſt for his Seruant. The Prodigall Sonne that acknowledged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a capitall ſinner againſt Heauen,<note place="margin">Luc. 18.10.13.</note> and
<pb facs="tcp:16347:16"/> his father, yet tooke vp good heart, &amp; went to his father. The <hi>Publicane</hi> ſmote his heart, &amp; pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced him ſelfe a ſinner at al hands; yet doubted he not to goe into the Temple to pray that his ſinnes might be forgiuen him Our Fayth ſhould be as the Fayth of <hi>Abraham, Who beleeued vnder hope, againſt hope,</hi> whatſoeuer our vnworthineſſe be, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to caſt downe the Sheild of the Fayth, which we haue towardes God, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth the place where the heart doth lie; and the Helme of Saluation, which coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth our head in the day of Battell. Fayth conſiſteth not ſo much in the ſenſe of Gods mercie, as in the apprehenſion of it; which appreheſion may be when there is no ſenſe of it.<note place="margin">Iob. 13.13.</note> This appeareth by <hi>Jobes</hi> example, where he ſayth, <hi>Though he ſlay mee, yet I will truſt in him:</hi> Where he ſheweth the force of his Fayth; yet what litle ſenſe he had of Gods mercie when hee ſo ſpake, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that hee ſayth immediatly after,<note place="margin">verſ. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore hidest thou thy face, and takest mee for thine enimie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Chriſtian ſometimes feeleth Fayth, and ſometimes feeleth none; that is, at that time when God firſt calleth him: and in the time of temptation. Heere a man may marueyle how one may be a Chriſtian, who hath no grace or goodneſſe in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. But it is no marueile, for it is with him,
<pb facs="tcp:16347:16"/> as it is with an Infant and young Child, who albeit yet hee hath not vſe of reaſon, yet is a creature reaſonable. A man that is in a ſwonde, hath no ſenſe of life; yet is he not dead. Fayth beleeueth the Promiſes of God, yea when we feele the contrarie; and in one contrarie, beleeueth an other. When we feele our ſinnes, wee beleeue our Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. When we feele our wretchedneſſe, we beleeue our Bleſſedneſſe. When we ſee nothing but eternall death before our eyes, it maketh vs beleeue our euerlaſting life. When we apprehend Gods anger, and feele him our enemie, it maketh vs to take hold of his louing kindneſſe, and to put our truſt in his fatherly goodneſſe. When Chriſt was forſaken of God, yet then hee called him his owne God; <hi>My God, my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. An other of their Obiections ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thus. There be many ſinnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to vs and ſo alſo vncertaine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be pardoned vnto vs.</p>
            <p>I anſwere, that they ground vpon a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation that will fayle them: For that a man can not be aſſured of the Pardon of his ſinnes, though ſome of them be vnknowne, is a falſe ground I make it plaine thus: It is in the caſe of Faith, as it is in that of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. But there may be true Repentance of ſinnes that are vnknowne. God will haue a particular repentance for particular kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen
<pb facs="tcp:16347:17"/> ſinnes: but where they are hidden and vnknowne to vs, hee taketh in good part at our handes a more broad and generall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. Of this we haue example in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> where he ſayth: <hi>Who can tell how oft hee offendeth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.12.</note> 
               <hi>O cleanſe thou mee from my ſecret faultes:</hi> Were it not thus, we were in wofull caſe: for neither <hi>Dauid,</hi> nor any one elſe, might be ſaued. For though <hi>Dauids</hi> repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce of his knowne ſinnes of Murder, and Adulterie appeareth vnto vs, yet wee finde it not in his Hiſtorie, or elſe where in holy Writte, that he particulerly repented his poligamie, his multiplicitie of Wiues and Concubines, which in all probabilitie with the cuſtome of the times, he drunke vp as men doe Wine out of Bowles with all fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitie, and ſo in the common reputation that it had, that it was no ſinne at all; it is likely enough of that, he repented not at all, eſpecially while he conſidered the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peremmencie of his perſon that he was a King, and by that had as good priuiledge and a libertie for this, as any common per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; yet becauſe Scripture determineth him a man choſen of God, a partie ſaued, it is peremptorily concluded, that this ſinne is pardoned. Therefore when God par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons the knowne ſinnes of man, whereof they doe in particuler repent, hee doth withall pardon the reſt that are vnknowne.
<pb facs="tcp:16347:17"/> It is vndeniable Diuinitie, that hee that certainely and truely knoweth that but one ſinne is pardoned him, hee hath before God, all his ſinnes pardoned him whether knowne or vnknowne: wherefore the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce of certaine ſinnes, cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice an vnfallible aſſurance of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of them all, and of his owne ſaluation.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Moreouer, whereas it is thus obiected vnto vs, that this propoſition of ours is not of the nature of an Article of our Fayth, to be ſo carryed away hand-ſmooth as that, and therefore that it can not perſwade vs as that.</p>
            <p>I anſwere, that the partie that will be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, muſt as ſteadfaſtly beleeue his Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the Articles of the <hi>Cree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e:</hi> Becauſe the Promiſe of life, and the Commaundement to beleeue it, and apply it to our ſelues; are indiuidually conioyned, and can not be deuided. Fayth ſpeaketh in the phraſe of <hi>Dauid: J am thine, O ſaue mee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> And it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth as <hi>Paul</hi> doth:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.38.</note> 
               <hi>J am perſwaded that neither Life or Death; neither Angels, Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities or Powers; or thinges preſent, or thinges to come, are euer able to ſeperate me from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſu our Lord.</hi> It tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth as the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi> in effect,<note place="margin">Cantic. 8.6.</note> in this zealous affect: <hi>Loue is ſtrong as death, Jealouſie is cruell as the Graue: The Coales thereof are fierie Coales, and a vehement flame. Much
<pb facs="tcp:16347:18"/> Water can not quench Loue, neither can the Floods drowne it. If a man ſhould giue all the ſubſtaunce of his houſe for Loue, they would great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contemne it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two thinges are required of vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue truly. Firſt, to vnderſtand a thing: Secondly, to giue our conſent vnto it, as vnto that which is true. Therefore Fayth is called, <hi>Tota copulatiua;</hi> and therefore hee that denieth but one poynt of Fayth, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hanocke of them altogeather.</p>
            <p>Againe, to beleeue is one thing; to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in this or that, is an other thing, and it containeth three actions of the perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing. 1. To know the thing. 2. To ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it. 3. To haue truſt in it. So that this knowledge is not naked, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. For the Diuels haue ſuch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; but it is more ſpeciall, by which wee know God not onely to be God; but to be my God, whereby I put my confidence in him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly I anſwere, that this Fayth whereby we are to beleeue our owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to conſider of it in the proper and true nature of it; is as certaine as that whereby we beleeue the Articles of Fayth. For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer wee pray for, according to Gods will, that wee are aſwell to beleeue that wee ſhall obtaine, as we doe beleeue the Articles of the Fayth. This is flatte by that which
<pb facs="tcp:16347:18"/> Chriſt ſayth:<note place="margin">Marc. 11.24.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoeuer yee deſire when yee pray, beleeue that yee ſhall haue it, and it ſhall be done vnto you.</hi> But wee put vp our Prayers for the remiſsion of our ſinnes, and for life euerlaſting: And therefore lay hold vpon the certaintie thereof, as vpon the Article of our Chriſtian Fayth. If God ſhould par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulerly ſay to thee or mee <hi>John,</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> beleeue in mee and thou ſhalt be ſaued: ſhould not this commaundement be as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible a binder, as any Article of our Fayth? But the Miniſter lawfully called in the name of God, when hee preacheth Gods word, it is all one as if God ſhould ſpeake from Heauen particularly vnto him, and make promiſe vnto him of eternall life: for wee are in legatiue commiſsion from God, to runne vpon this his arrant vnto you, according to that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth: <hi>Now then are we Ambaſsadours for Christ:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>as though God did beſeech you through vs, wee pray you in Chriſtes ſtead, that yee be reconciled to God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4.16.</note> We come to the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h one of Grace,</hi> in the certaintie of fayth <hi>boldly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10 35.</note> 
               <hi>that we may receiue Mercie, &amp; find Grace, to helpe in time of need.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.</note> And wee <hi>Caſt not away that confidence which hath great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of reward.</hi> Our Fayth is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Cognitio a,</hi> but in <hi>Agnition,</hi> likewiſe, in
<pb facs="tcp:16347:19"/> acknowledgement, as well as in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Inquiſitiue fellowes, like <hi>Nichode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 3.</note> puts vp queſtions; <hi>How can this thing be?</hi> or as the <hi>Jewes,</hi> that came in properly with their ſpoake,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 6.</note> 
               <hi>How can he giue vs his fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh to eate?</hi> by beeing thus buſie, euidently doe bewray themſelues, that they doe not beleeue. Wee may lawfully aske of the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> how this may bee, that wee may be inſtructed? But we may not come with Interrogatories in the caſe, to nouriſh doubtinges.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, albeit Fayth it ſelfe be the ſame, and common to all; yet is it not ſo in the meaſure of it: But in ſome, it is of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in ſome of leſſer quantitie; <hi>As God hath dealt to euery man the meaſure of Fayth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.3.</note> The Seede that was throwne vpon the good Ground, came not vp alike, but in ſeuerall plottes verie diſproportionably, in ſome thirtie, in ſome ſixtie, in ſome an hundred fold.</p>
            <p>It is with Fayth as it is with the body of man. Firſt we are Infantes, then we increaſe in yeares and ſtrength: We are firſt Infants in Chriſt Ieſu, and by degrees grow from Grace to Grace, vntill wee come at laſt to that height &amp; ſtrength, as wee grow ſtrong in the Fayth with <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a Poſitiue, and a Superlatiue Fayth. The Poſitiue is that, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:16347:19"/> is tearmed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>A litle Fayth, <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
               </hi> rather then <hi>Quantum,</hi> ſampled by our Sauiour to the graine of Muſtard ſeed, the leaſt of all Seedes;<note place="margin">Math. 17.20.</note> which being put into the ground, groweth into, Firſt, an Hearbe. 2. the greateſt of all Hearbes, 3. yea into a Tree 4. into ſuch a broad Tree as the Birdes of the Heauen make their neſtes in the branches thereof; compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Prophet <hi>Iſay,</hi> to ſmoakie Flaxe.<note place="margin">Iſa. 42.3.</note> The Superlatiue Fayth is that, which is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>An abſolute Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance,</hi> as not being onely a certaine and true perſwaſion, but plenarie &amp; compleate. But this leaſt degree of Fayth of this Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue kind, this beginning or rudiment of Fayth, this ſmoakie Flaxe which hath no Fire in it, of that weakneſſe as it giueth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heate nor light; Chriſt will not quench, but will make it gather ſtrength, and waxe into a Fire; ſo that we will doe our part, and vſe the meanes that ſerue to increaſe it, by diligent meditation vpon the word of God, earneſt and ardent Prayer, and ſuch other holy exerciſes, appertaining to the furtheraunce of our Fayth.</p>
            <p>This litle Fayth may be thus deſcribed; when one in the humilitie of his heart hath not yet a ſenſe of the certaintie of the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his ſinnes, and yet notwithſtanding perſwadeth him ſelfe that they are ſuch as
<pb facs="tcp:16347:20"/> may be forgiuen him, his ſoule deſyring forgiueneſſe of them, and therefore prayeth vnto God that he would forgiue them, and giue him ſtrength euer after to forſake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>The Superlatiue Fayth is the full ſtrength and maturitie of Fayth, which diſſolueth all doubtes, and is not onely in nature cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, but alſo a large and plentifull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of Gods mercie in Chriſt; of which we gaue you examples before in <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi> By the firſt Fayth intricated with doubts, men doe as certainly beleeue their Adoption, as the Articles of their Fayth; but not ſo firmely and fully. By this larger Fayth, remiſsion of ſinnes is not onely as certainely, but alſo as fully beleeued, as any Article of Fayth.</p>
            <p>To end Obiections, &amp; ſo our firſt Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, we will iuſtifie our Doctrine by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages of Fathers, becauſe it is obiected to vs by our Aduerſaries, that this poynt of the infallible and ſpeciall certaintie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ction is generally diſauowed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mned by the Fathers; though otherwiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ters of Fayth, wee hang not on their ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>enes the word of God, being the onely rule and ſquare of our beliefe. <hi>Secur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> estote <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> et ſanguis,</hi> ſayth <hi>Tertullian;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ctione.</note> Let fleſh and blood be ſecure and take out their <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s est.</hi> Would ye know why wee ſhould be ſecure? <hi>Ambroſe</hi> telleth you that you
<pb facs="tcp:16347:20"/> haue good cauſe ſo to be,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cap. 4. et. 5. ad Rom.</note> 
               <hi>Securj quia credunt ſecurj <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xemplo Abrahamae:</hi> They are ſecure, becauſe they doe beleeue, they are ſecure af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the example of <hi>Abraham.</hi> So doth S. <hi>Aug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stine:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> domini ſerm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> de pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſsi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e;</hi> Secure in our Pardon, ſecure in the Promiſe that is made to vs. To whom ſubſcribeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">De quadrip. in. tit. pag. 2. 3</note> as he is cited by <hi>Caſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, In pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>mtione veniae ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> In the penitent perſon, a certaine ſecuritie is begotten out of the preſumption of a Pardon. And <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 39.</note> liketh well this Preſumption, <hi>Thou praeſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed mo erata;</hi> It is a good Preſumption, but moderate. Heare further what <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de verbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Domin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſermo. 7.</note> ſayth; <hi>Jnter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>go te (peccator) credis ne Christo velno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> credo, quia creus? Quod liberè <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oteſt tibere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re omnia tua pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> I demaund of thee (O ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,) Beleeueſt thou in Chriſt or not? Thou telleſt me thou beleeueſt. I aske next, what doeſt thou beleeue? Thou anſwereſt, that hee can pardon thee all thy ſinnes. Thou haſt that which thou beleeueſt. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaketh effectually to our cauſe in hand,<note place="margin">Bernard. ſerm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. nuat. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> thus; <hi>Si cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as peccata tua non p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſse ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> raſi percunt contre q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> peccasi, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ages, ſed vl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rius progrede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, et cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cum remiſiſs tibi p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata tit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Hoc eſt teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>omiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od ſpiritus ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctus dat in cordibus noſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is, dicens peccat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tua remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuntur tibi. Nam ſic Apoſtolus putat hominem
<pb facs="tcp:16347:21"/> Juſtifica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>j gratis per ſi em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> If thou beleeueſt that thy ſinnes can not be blotted out, but onely by him againſt whom thou haſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, thou doeſt well: But proceed further, and beleeue that hee hath forgiuen thee thy ſinnes: For this is this witneſſe, that the Spirit of God maketh in our hearts, ſaying, Thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee; for ſo the Apoſtle taketh a man to be iuſtified freely by Fayth. The <hi>Papiſtes</hi> beeing choked with this place, fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ble vp this anſwere; that <hi>Bernard</hi> doth not ſay, that we ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the remiſsion of our ſinnes abſolutly withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reſpect of workes; but that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth our repentance as a ſigne by which this Perſwaſion is wrought. But wee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere them that he doth perſpicuouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerre, that the generall Fayth, by which the fundamentall matters of Religion are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, is onely the Beginning, and Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Fayth; and therefore ſufficeth not, vnleſſe we goe further, and apply by Fayth this Grace of God vnto our ſelues, ſimply without reference to any tradition of our ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ut us Felix</hi> ſingeth the ſame ſonge with the former; <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſpe futurae reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is:</hi> Wee are ſecure vnder hope of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection to come. <hi>Cornelius</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cornelius Bitontius, in cap. 8. an Rom.</note> Biſhop of <hi>Bitonto,</hi> one of their owne ſide, ſpeaketh loudly and liberally for vs, in this wiſe:
<pb facs="tcp:16347:21"/> 
               <hi>Qui in Chriſto Ieſu ſunt, nihil habent, vnde timere debent:</hi> They that are in Chriſt Ieſu, haue nothing whereof they ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayde, <hi>Si quidem ſecuri ſunt de ſalute,</hi> Inaſmuch as they are ſecure of their ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antonius Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anton. Mari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> in the Chapter hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at <hi>Trent,</hi> durſt ſtand foorth and preach not onely of the doctrine of the certaintie of Saluation, but alſo of our ſecuritie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſpeaking in this wiſe: <hi>Ab operum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gloria auerſi, in illius patris elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia et voluntate, et in perpetuum conqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Item, indubitationis labirintho non errant, qui per Chriſtum adepti ſunt Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſed in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>curitate mentis, in pace conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae, in laetitia cordis audent dicere, Abha pater:</hi> Wee wholly draw our mindes from any confidence in our owne workes, and repoſe our truſt in the louing kindneſſe and goodwill of our heauenly Father for euer. Alſo, they erre not in the maze of miſtruſt, who haue obteined righteouſneſſe through Chriſt, but they date boldly ſay in the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Minde, peace of Conſcience, ioy of Heart, <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a</hi> Father.</p>
            <p>The ſame Doctor in the ſame Councell,<note place="margin">Concil. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Act 1. Anno. 1546.</note> was thus peremptorie in this poynt, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of his owne Fayth herein on this wiſe.
<pb facs="tcp:16347:22"/> 
               <hi>Si Caelum ruat, ſi Terra euaneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at, ſi Orbis diſsoluatur, praeceps ego in eum erectus ero: ſi Angelus de caelo aliud mihi perſuad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re contendat, dicam illi, mathema: O faelicem Chriſtiam p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is fiducia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> Though Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſhould paſſe away, the Earth conſume to nothing, and the whole World ſhould be diſſolued, I ſhall erect my ſelfe towardes him. And though an Angelicall Doctor from heauen ſhould goe about to perſwade me otherwiſe, I ſhould tell to his head, that he is accurſed. O the happie aſſurance of a Chriſtian ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Oratione.</note>The very <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>entine</hi> Catechiſme thus ſpeaketh in our cauſe: <hi>Fides eſt quae preces fundit, preces facit, vt omni dubitatione ſublata, ſtabilis a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rma ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t fides:</hi> It is Fayth that powreth out Praiers, conceiueth Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that all diſtruſt remooued, our Fayth might be firme and ſtable.</p>
            <p>Some of the beſt of the bunch of <hi>Papi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes</hi> doe preach, and publiſh this true certaintie, and holy ſecuritie that wee ſpeake of. At <hi>Tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> this cauſe hath been throughly can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſed, not by <hi>vollie</hi> of wordes, but by vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of Bookes. <hi>Cathar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> is our Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion againſt <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>minicus Soto;</hi> in which Booke of his, he telleth vs, how the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are diuided in this Doctrine; how they preferre their owne Reaſons, and their
<pb facs="tcp:16347:22"/> vaine Philoſophie, before the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſo turne aſide out of the right way. They diſtaſte theſe wordes of Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and Certaintie: but they ſhould relliſe them the better, if they would beare in minde this text out of <hi>Jſaiah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 32.17.</note> 
               <hi>The worke of righteouſneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhalbe peace, euen the worke of Iuſtice, and quietneſse, and aſſuraunce for euer.</hi> They are tearmes the Fathers commonly take vp, as in the precedent inſtances you haue heard. <hi>Cyprian</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyp. de mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talit. ſerm. 4.</note> admireth we ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſpeake or thinke, where he ſaith: <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t tu dubitas, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> flactuas? Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt Deum omnino non noſcere. Hoc eſt Chriſtum, credentium magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum, peccato incredulitatis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffendere. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c eſt in E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cleſia construtum, fidem in domo fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> Doeſt thou doubt and wauer? This is altogeather not to know God. This is to diſpleaſe Chriſt the Maiſter of the Fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, with the ſinne of Incredulitie. This is to be in the Church, and to denie the Fayth in the very Houſe of Fayth.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of the indiuiduall ſocietie that is betweene the Fleſh and the Spirit, doubts and quaimes muſt often ariſe and come vpon our heartes, and trouble our Fayth. Incredulitie betweene times, will aſſault euery man; when his Fayth is at the beſt, the ſenſuall part of man euer coueting againſt the Spirit; but Fayth will quiet all theſe brawles and broyles at the laſt, be our Faith
<pb facs="tcp:16347:23"/> neuer ſo eclipſed with Cloudes, toſſed with Tempeſtes, winnowed by Sathan, driuen at by the Dartes, and all the fierie Dartes of the Deuill; though brought into an agonie, bloodie ſweate, and extaſie, as Chriſt was in the Garden, and on the Croſſe; yea, though almoſt brought to vtter deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the very brimme and introduction into the Hell of the damned: then God ſeemeth to ſtand a farre off, and to hide him ſelfe in the needfull time of trouble: to ſtop his eares with Waxe, and not to heare vs, though we make many Prayers: to hold his hand ſtill in his booſome, and not to plucke it out in our extremities, Fayth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the victorie that ouercommeth the whole World: and ſo wee conclude this firſt Queſtion; Whether one may be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine or his particuler Election, affirmatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as ye haue heard, and put it out of queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with this ioyfull acclamation of the Prophet; <hi>Bleſſed be God that hath ſhewed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo great kindneſſe in a ſtrong citie:</hi> That hath ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs in this inuincible fortreſſe of Fayth, ſo that we may caſt out our Gantlet, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke all our enemies to the field, and to the foyle; ſo that neither Life nor Death, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Principalities nor Powers, thinges preſent nor things to come, nor any things elſe in the nature of thinges can make a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration betweene God and vs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16347:23"/>
            <p>The ſecond Queſtion now vnder our deciſion, is; How our particular Election may be knowne?</p>
            <p>There be two wayes of knowing it. 1 Firſt, by going vp as it were to Heauen, there to prie into the very priuities of God: and then to come downe, and to come into our ſelues. But we diſclaime this courſe, as pernicious &amp; perilous, God hauing drawne Curtaines of blacke Cloudes and Darknes ouer his Tabernacle round about him:<note place="margin">Bernar. ſerm. 31. in Cantica.</note> 
               <hi>Ad Deum accedendum non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>uendu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> Wee may come to God, but not, <hi>Concitate c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>u prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter viam,</hi> Wee muſt not ruſh violently into his preſence Chamber. 2. Secondly, by the contrarie, by deſcending into our heartes, by going vp from our ſelues to Gods eternall Counſaile. This is the way chalked out vnto vs, which we may ſafely walke; which teacheth vs by tokens in our ſelues, to gather what was the eternall Counſaile of God touching our ſaluation. Theſe tokens are two; not taken from the Primitiue cauſes of our Election: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the latter effectes thereof. 1. The teſtimonie of Gods Spirit. 2. The workes of our Sanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> This is proofe enough in Law: For the Law hath ſpoken it: <hi>In the mouthes of two or three Witneſses ſhall euery thing be confirmed.</hi> The Spirit of God is a Witneſſe for the nonce, the beſt that is in
<pb facs="tcp:16347:24"/> Heauen, ſealing the certaintie of adoption in our heartes, with the ſinger of his grace, it beeing further confirmed vnto vs, vnder the Signet of the blood of the Lambe. An inferiour Witneſſe by farre, might haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſufficiently, for the perſwaſion of this matter. As an Angell from Heauen, addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Man, and diſpatched to our Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the times of old<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: Nay, If a King out of his Throne ſhould commende a Man, what Subiect durſt oppoſe himſelfe to that opinion? Now if wee receiue the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Angell, or Man, that is great: The teſtimonie of God, is greater, as the ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt eſſence, our beſt Schoolemaiſter that teacheth vs to pray, that holdeth vp ſuch as pray by the head, by the hand of his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: That is as good as his word, and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his promiſe for euer, that witneſſeth the ſame by his inward motions, and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in our heartes. An Angell, for all his Spirituall intelligence,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.10.</note> muſt not compare in any ſort with the holy ghoſt in knowledge of the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>earchable ſecrets of God: The Holy Ghoſt can leſſe deceiue vs,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.13.</note> then an Angell, as beeing the vncreated trueth it ſelfe, which leadeth into all trueth: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, the teſtimonie he perfourmeth, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde all compariſon, becauſe it reſteth not in the care, ſo to runne into the ayre, but keepeth reſidence in our Reynes, and
<pb facs="tcp:16347:24"/> Veines, hath a Chayer in our heartes, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſsing to our Spirits, that we are the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, by ſpeaking, ſhewing foorth his power, and by praying in vs. Adde heereto, that this Spirit hath indiuiduall commerce with our Spirit, neuer departeth from vs: Hee taketh not vp the Temples of our bodyes as an Inne for a ſhort time, and be gone; but as an Houſe, wherein he is minded to continue, aſſuming to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the whole regiment of them; as a Lord that commeth to dwell in an Houſe, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth of that Houſe after his owne pleaſure. Now as touching his Subſtaunce hee dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not in vs; the infinite Spirit of God being not to be cooped vp in the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and ſtraight Roomes of the Bodie, and Soule of man, but onely in his ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue power with vs, hee keepeth his reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Papistes</hi> vildly derogate from the ſufficiencie of this Teſtimonie, while they mince and miniſh it alter their owne man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; while they frame, in the forge of their Fancies this deuiſe, that this Witneſſe of our Adoption is onely in ſome comfortable ſenſe and feeling of Gods fauour, being ſuch as is weake, and oft times deceiueable. But by their leaue, it is much more then a bare and naked feeling of Gods ſauour: For it is called in holy Scripture, <hi>The Pledge
<pb facs="tcp:16347:25"/> and Earnest</hi> of Gods Spirit in our heartes;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.22.</note> and therefore it is ſufficient to preuent and take away all arguments of doubting: as in a Bargaine and ſtipulation the <hi>Earnest</hi> that is giuen is the binder of the Bargaine on both ſides, and makes it out of que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth, That the Teſtimonie of the Spirit, is a moſt ſure Teſtimonie.</p>
            <p>As concerning this Teſtimonie of the Spirit of God, two Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtions would be ſcanned. 1. How it may be diſtinguiſhed from the Spirit of Illuſion, that is, from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. 2. By what meanes the Spirit of God giueth a particuler teſtimonie in a Mans conſcience, of his certaine election.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt, wee are to know, that as there is a certaine perſwaſion of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour from the Spirit of God: So Sathan hath his ſleightes, whereby he ſoweth Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of Preſumption to mens Elbowes, ſuggeſting pleaſinges and leaſings vnto vs. This Preſumption commeth to vs by kind, as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are men, as a naturall and ineuitable euill, which hath a ſhew of Fayth, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth the power of it. And this counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feite-mocke qualitie of pretended Fayth, is more common then the true and liuely Fayth indeed. This wee ſee dayly in the common careleſſe people: For if any of them ſhall be asked, what they thinke of themſelues, whether they ſhall be ſaued or
<pb facs="tcp:16347:25"/> no? they will wipe their mouths with their Handkerchiefe, and ſay, yea, without all doubt; ſo that if there were but few in the Countrie to be ſaued they perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that themſelues are thoſe perſons: For why, he hath alwayes orderly kept his Church, euermore beleeued, and haue done no man wrong: Theſe, and ſuch like miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſhioned Fancies, eaſily with ſuch vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, goe for good and lawfull Fayth. But ſuch m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n would be vnmasked, and this M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſter that couereth their eyes and lead them blindfold, is to be taken from them. Wherefore I anſwere to the Queſtion, That the Spirit of God is many wayes to be decerned from the Spirit of Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 1. Firſt, by a full perſwaſion the ſpirit of God giueth: for the holy Ghoſt doth not barely word it, but throughly worketh it, by force of perſwaſion; which is not in the power of Nature ſo to doe. 2. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the manner of Perſwaſion: for the holy Ghoſt diſputeth not from the workes or worthineſſe of man; he draweth not the waters of life vnto vs, from ſuch ſhallow Welles, but he draweth deeper then euer <hi>Iacobs</hi> Well was, euen from the profound and bottomleſſe Fountaine of Gods loue and fauour towardes vs; and no other kind of Logicke doth he vſe with vs. This is a courſe that Sathan can not skill on; he hath
<pb facs="tcp:16347:26"/> no will vnto it: it is quite croſſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie vnto him. 3. Thirdly, by the effects of that Teſtimonie: For the Perſwaſion that ariſeth from Preſumption, is cold and dead; but that which hath deſcenſe from the Spirit of God, is liuely in operation: for ſuch as are poſſeſſed with this Perſwaſion, that they are the Elected &amp; Adopted Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, they will loue God, repoſe their truſt in him, call vpon his name &amp; that with the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r whole heartes: and in regard of their loue to him, they will loath ſinne, and euery thing elſe that agreeth not with his will The Effectes whereby wee know the true Spirit from the counterfeit, are two; noted downe by <hi>Paul,</hi> where he ſayth; <hi>The Spirit maketh vs cry, Abba</hi> (that is) <hi>Father.</hi> The firſt, is to pray with ſuch intention of Minde, and contention of Sinnewes and Sides, with groanes and ſighes, as though a man would fill Heauen and Earth: A prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall knowne marke of the Spirit of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>option, neuer to be found in the Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous rechleſſe ſort, who pray but at Good times; and when they pray, they heare not their Prayers, their Spirit dieth in the Ayre, before it can pierce the Cloudes, and aſcend vp to Heauen where God is. The Church hath their Bodyes, but their Heartes are at home. They bleat out the Lords Prayer, the Creede, and ten Commandements, with
<pb facs="tcp:16347:26"/> their lippes: but their God is their Gold, their mindes are on their Mony-bagges, or elſe they wander in their extrauagant thoughts, as the Prodigall Sonne <hi>In longin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m regionem,</hi> in a farre Countrie. They pray as though their heartes and tongues were ſtrangers; drawing neere him with their lippes, but ſtanding along aloofe off with their heartes; praying, &amp; in the meane while leauing their Spirit aſleepe: or if they awake it, they leaue it, as Chriſt did his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples for the time. Their Altar is without Fire, their Prayers without feruour, their Wordes without intention, the outward action of their bodies without the conſent of their inner affections.</p>
            <p>The ſecond effect is the Affect of Heart, anſwerable in nature to that which is in Children towardes their Parents; which is an affection of loue, reuerence, obedience, thankfulneſſe: For they call not vpon him as vpon a skarlot and grimme Iudge, but they come to him in his familiar name, <hi>Abba,</hi> that is, a gracious &amp; mercifull Father. Now ſuch as are not of the right Spirit, they can not in trueth come to him in this name. Finally, where the teſtimonie of the Spirit is, many other graces of the Spirit are with it: for it will not be ſolitarie, as when one branch of a Tree ſprouteth, the reſt ſprout
<pb facs="tcp:16347:27"/> out with it. Further, learne thus to know them aſunder, &amp; to put difference betweene the Spirit, and Preſumption. 1. Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is an inborne qualitie, which wee ſucke from our Mothers: but the witneſſe of the Spirit is ſupernaturall 2. Preſumption is in them, that recke not of the ordinarie meanes that make to their ſaluation. But they that are of the Spirit, chearefully imbrace them, &amp; take care to follow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; they reuerently &amp; religiouſly heare the word of God. 3 Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptio is in ſuch that vſe not to call on the name of God: but the Spirit of God is the Spirit of Prayer, teaching vs to pray with teares not able to be expreſſed. Preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is lincked with Looſeneſſe of life: the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit worketh vs in a new mould,<note place="margin">Mat 2, 22.</note> 
               <hi>Mutatus ab illo Hectore,</hi> cleane contrary to that we were before, and warneth vs, with the Wiſe-men of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> not againe to returne to <hi>Herods</hi> Court, to our old Byas; but by caſting off our old conuerſation, as the Eagle doth her bill, to turne into our country an other way. Preſumption is peremptorie, and maketh a man to ſtand vpon his Slippers to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident vp to the throate, and neuer once to caſt any doubt of our well doing, whereas the conſciences of the godly are oft times perplexed, and troubled with doubtes, yea, now and then ſurcharged, &amp; ouerwhelmed
<pb facs="tcp:16347:27"/> with them. Preſumption will faile vs at a dead lift, and giue vs the ſlippe in the need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full time of trouble, in the houre of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and death. But the Spirit of God ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth cloſe to vs, and continueth with vs for euer and euer.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Wee come to the handling of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond poynt, how the Spirit witneſſeth our Adoption. For that it witneſſeth the ſame vnto vs, this Scripture concludeth it, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other Authorities of Scripture beſide, flatly confirme it. Our Heartes are wholly in the hands of the Spirit, to rule &amp; gouerne them as ſeemeth beſt to him. This Rule of his, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth chiefely in the certaine reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led knowledge of our attonement with the Father in Chriſt. Hereof ſpeaketh the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jſaiah,</hi> thus: <hi>By his knowledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 53 11.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall my righteous Seruant iuſtifie in my.</hi> Of this ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth our Sauiour where he ſayth;<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.3.</note> 
               <hi>This is life eternall, that they know thee to be the onely verie GOD, and whom thou haſt ſent, Ieſus Christ.</hi> This knowledge is not that which is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: for ſo the Deuils might be ſaued; but it is that which is particuler, by which a man commeth to know, that God is his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Chriſt his Redeemer, the Holy Ghoſt his Sanctifier and Comforter. This know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is the peculiar worke of the Spirit, as this Text teacheth, as this other the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:16347:28"/> mouth deliuereth of the ſame nature: <hi>Wee haue receiued not the Spirit of the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>but the Spirite which is of God, that wee might know the things that are giuen to vs of God.</hi> Now three manner of wayes, doth the Spirit make vs priuie to this counſaile of God. 1. By his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Inſpiration 2 By his outward Word. 3. Inwardly, &amp; outwardly; by inward, and outward effects. By his Spirit he did inſpire the Prophetes, and open many thinges to come. And Chriſt ſayd to his Apoſtles, as concerning the Holy ghoſt; <hi>He ſhall lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you into all trueth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 16.13.</note> By his Word he ſpake vnto the Prophets; and by his Word in like manner he teacheth vs his Will. Alſo by diuers ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes he declareth either his Mercie, or his Iuſtice; as it is well knowne. The ſame is to be thought of the reuealing of his Election; to witte, that God reuealeth the ſame to the Elect, by the Spirit, by the Word, &amp; by the moſt aſſured effectes of his Predeſtination: We are now to ſpeake of them ſeuerally in their order.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By inward inſpiration we haue inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our certaine Election; by which our mindes are illuminated, and it is reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto vs, that wee are from all eternitie Predeſtinated into this Adoption of his Son-ſhip. All the Elect are owners of this Grace, as now actually made the Sonnes of
<pb facs="tcp:16347:28"/> God by Fayth, regenerated and new borne by the Holy ghoſt, &amp; ingrafted into Chriſt. So the Apoſtle ſaith;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>If any man hath not the ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit of Chriſt, he is not his.</hi> Whoſoeuer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is of Chriſt, &amp; is ingrafted into Chriſt, muſt needes, <hi>ipſo f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> haue the Spirit of Chriſt Now, whoſoeuer haue receiued and haue this ſpirit of Chriſt, the ſpirit of God teſtifieth to their mindes, that they are the ſonnes of God &amp; he maketh them to ſpeake in the language of Children, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ba,</hi> that is, Father. And it is a certaine caſe, that none is renewed by the ſpirit of God, who is not peremptorily perſwaded, that God is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his moſt louing and gracious Father, and ſo call vpon him, by that ſweete &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall name. Therfore though all men in that they are aſſured by the certaintie of Fayth, that God is their Father, and they are his Sonnes, do not thereby argue and conclude that they are elected to eternall life: yet all men indeed haue thereby a moſt ſure cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate of their Election to the ſtate of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; becauſe if they be the Sonnes of God, it followeth by due conſequent, that they alſo be the heires of eternall life. Let this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie appeare euident by way of demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, in this manner. Whoſoeuer call vpon God, and in their heartes cry, <hi>Abba</hi> Father; it is certaine, that ſuch be the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb facs="tcp:16347:29"/> of God, and that this cry of theirs is from the gift &amp; motion of the ſpirit of God. But whoſoeuer are the Sonnes of God, are alſo inheritours of life euerlaſting, and they are predeſtinated into the adoption of his children. Therefore it cannot otherwiſe be, but that all ſuch as are perſwaded by the ſpirit of God, that they are the Sonnes of God, ſhould be predeſtinated to eternall life &amp; be throughly perſwaded in the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond meanes whereby we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the knowledge of our Election, is his outward Word, not any particular Word by which hee doth outwardly in priuate and proper manner ſuggeſt to any man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly his Election, but the generall word of the Goſpell; in the which Chriſt calleth all them which beleeue in him, Elect. For albeit he giueth vs no ſuch plaine &amp; parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer propoſition as this is, <hi>Thou art Elected vnto euerlaſting life;</hi> yet no leſſe is concluded in the heartes of the Elect in ſuch Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmes as are generall, euen as each particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler man is determined capable of reaſon, by the vniuerſalitie of this Axiome, <hi>Euery man liuing is a creature reaſonable,</hi> though the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption be ſuppreſſed. This therefore is the courſe that God taketh with vs: He hath choſen all, and euery one, whom he decreed to be faythfull heyres of ſaluation. And this
<pb facs="tcp:16347:29"/> maine Maxime in tearmes generall, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed by the Apoſtles at the Standard, to all that are Elect. The Propoſition in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralitie ſtandeth thus; <hi>All the Faythfull are elected to euerlaſting life.</hi> Heere the word ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and medleth not with the <hi>Miner.</hi> Now heere God effecteth by Fayth, that hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth on vs, that wee make the <hi>Minor</hi> in our mindes in this manner; <hi>But I am of the fellowſhip of the faythfull,</hi> as feeling that I truly beleeue in Chriſt. How commeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now thy cauſe to be concluded, that thou art Predeſtinated to eternitie of glory? Truely by God, that giueth the propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Goſpell, and by working thine heart with the worke of faith, which hee worketh in thee, to goe on with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</p>
            <p>It is therefore manifeſt, that God, by the word of the Ghoſpell, where he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth all the faythfull to be elected, that he doth reueale his particuler election, to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that is of the fayth: Onely it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth euery Beleeuer in hand, that as often as hee heareth the generall Propoſition, hee make the Aſſumption, and inferre it in the nicke, and vpon the necke of it: And ſo doth the Lord reueale to euery man, his ſpeciall malediction, by this generall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures enuntiation: <hi>Curſed be euery one that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth
<pb facs="tcp:16347:30"/> not in all thinges, which are written in this Bo ke.</hi> Though hee doth not come to tell euery man in his eare, that hee, and hee, is accurſed: For this may euery one gather of himſelfe, his conſcience telling him, that he hath ſtarted from the Statutes of God, like a broken Bowe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third kind of meanes, by which God vnfouldeth and layeth open to vs our ſtate of Saluation, is the effectes in vs aſwell inward at outward effectually aſſuring the ſame vnto vs in a double reſpect 1. Firſt, becauſe theſe effectes are ſuch as God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them to none, but onely to the Elect. 2 Next, for that they are not ſimply the effectes of Election, but alſo ſuch, and ſuch as they be, the engrauen Seales and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Stampe thereof. For God is like to the Sunne to vs. The Sunne while it ſtriketh vs with his radiant Beames, and in a manner looketh vs on the face, leaueth ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion of his light in our eyes, as wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally by the participation of the ſame light, ſee the Sunne it ſelfe, &amp; the very light thereof: For the light of the Sunne &amp; the beames thereof ſent downe vpon vs, reflect againe vpon the Sunne it ſelfe. So the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge of God in which from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, he did, &amp; would acknowledge vs for his owne, is ſo in God, as in it ſelfe, is not to
<pb facs="tcp:16347:30"/> be ſeene of vs: but yet as God acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs to be his, and engraueth the Forme and Image of this knowledge in vs that are elected he bringeth it to paſſe, as wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this God for our onely true God, and bid all other farewell. So that God f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt looketh downe from Heauen on vs, and acknowledgeth vs; and ſo by commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this knowledge &amp; light vnto vs, we are thereby made to know him againe. Hereto ſerueth that which Chriſt ſayth: <hi>J know my Sheepe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.14.</note> and immediatly inferreth thereupon, <hi>I am knowne of mine:</hi> As if hee ſhould haue ſayd, While I know them for my Sheepe, and marke them out as Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardes doe their Sheepe with a red ſtroake euen of my redde blood, I make them on the other ſide by the participation of my knowledge, that they acknowledge me for their Shepheard. The ſame learning the Apoſtle giues the <hi>Galathians,</hi> where he faith, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing yee k ow God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4.9.</note> 
               <hi>yee rather are knowne of God. &amp;c.</hi> Where hee would haue the <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> know, that all their knowledge hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayne,</hi> from the foreknowledge that God had of them.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid of the Loue of God, in which he loued vs in Chriſt, before the ground-worke of the World was layde; which loue of vs, is more then Adamantine,
<pb facs="tcp:16347:31"/> and hath been the onely Loadſtone to draw our loue by retaliation vnto him. For Gods loue to vs being eternall, and to eternall life, muſt beget in time in vs, a loue ſomewhat like ſeruing to the eternitie of his glory; whereto pertaineth theſe wordes of S. <hi>John, Not that wee loued God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>but that hee firſt loued vs;</hi> making our loue, the conſequent of his loue. So that by the ſinceere loue we beare towardes him, we conſider of the latitude, and qualitie of that loue, wherewith God in Chriſt from all eternitie hath proſecuted vs. Now what is all this his Loue, but our Election?</p>
            <p>Now that none is elected vnto life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, who beare not in due time theſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes and cognizances of their Election about them, it is manifeſt by ſuch Scripture places, which deale in the poynt of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination. The holy Apoſtle telleth vs, that wee were elected; that wee ſhould be holy and without blame.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> And hee further informeth vs; that ſuch whom God Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinateth, are likewiſe Called, and Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and ſo conſequently qualified with Fayth, and the knowledge of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they acknowledge God for their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and with loue, whereby they imbrace him as their Father: And finally, with good will and ſetled reſolution,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note> conſtantly
<pb facs="tcp:16347:31"/> and continually to ſeeke his glorie.</p>
            <p>But we come to the effectes, by which we come to the knowledge of the cauſes. They are of two ſortes. 1. Such as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily appertaine to all, without which they are not capable of eternall life. 2. Such as are annexed, as dependances, and appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances thereunto. Of the firſt ſort, are, 1. Chriſt, as Mediator and Prieſt, and his obedience and righteouſneſſe, (for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt, there is no ſaluation.) 2. Our ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall Vocation to Chriſt by the holy Spirit, and the coniunctaunces thereof, our Iuſtification, and ſo our Regeneration therevpon. Theſe foure; Predeſtination, Vocation, Iuſtification, Glorification, are ſo coadunited and coanimated togeather, as they cannot be diuided. And ſo no man can be Glorified, who is not Iuſtified: and no man can be Iuſtified, that is not firſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually Called; as no man can be ſo called, who is not Predeſtinated. Without theſe meanes, no not the very Infants, can attaine to this end of their endleſſe Glorie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore inwardly all the Elect children by the Holy ghoſt in their kind, are Called, and Iuſtified; that they may be likewiſe Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified.</p>
            <p>Of the Second ſort, which Infantes by reaſon of their age, can not haue, which
<pb facs="tcp:16347:32"/> notwithſtanding follow the reſt of the Elect, though in ſome they are more forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in ſome more infirme; in ſome more, in otherſome leſſe, are ſuch as follow actuall and habituall Fayth. 1 Hearing of the Word. 2 Hatred of Sinne, Loue of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. 3 Patience in aduerſitie. 4 En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to doe good Workes: Wherefore we ſay, that ſuch as are Elected to this end, are therewithall Predeſtinated vnto the meanes that tend to this end: For Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is not onely of the end, but alſo of the meanes that ſerue therevnto. All, as well the end as the meanes, are the effectes of Predeſtination. Wherefore rightly ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>Praediſtinatio est praeparatio beneficiorii D j, quibus cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſine liberantur qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>antur:</hi> Predeſtination is a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the benefites of God, by which they are moſt certainely deliuered, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer are deliuered.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Gift of God (the effect of Predeſtination) is Chriſt Ieſus, with his Obedience, Merites, Death, Reſurrection, Glorie; as hee is ordained Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Father and vs, and the head of all the Elect, and ſo the Head &amp; Fountaine of all the manifold Graces of God, from the flowing ſtreame of his free Predeſtination powred vpon vs: For the effectes of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination,
<pb facs="tcp:16347:32"/> are ſo ordinate, and ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate one to the other, as thoſe that haue precedencie, giue their efficiencie and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie to their fellowes. Wherfore Chriſt being the formoſt effect of Election, hee is the cauſe of all the reſt, from whom, and by whom they are all the companie of them conuayed, and communicated vnto vs. Wherefore worthily the Apoſtle in his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> the firſt Chapter,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> layeth vs downe theſe Leſſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That we are Choſen in Chriſt,<note place="margin">verſ. 5.</note> as it were in the head, that wee ſhould be his members.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That hee hath Predeſtinated vs to Adoption, &amp; filiation; but wee are adopted into this Son-ſhip in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Gal. 4 6.</note> the firſt borne of manie Brethren; and by the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid filiation, we are really &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Sonnes of God, endowed with his Spirit, by which wee are regenerated.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">verſ. 6.</note> That we are made freely accepted to God in Chriſt his beloued.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That in the ſame Chriſt,<note place="margin">verſ. 7.</note> we haue our Redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, through his Blood of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Couenant, euen the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes; as all Wiſedome and Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding beſide.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Finally, that all thinges in him,<note place="margin">verſ. 8.</note> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled togeather, as well the thinges in
<pb facs="tcp:16347:33"/> Heauen,<note place="margin">Gal. 4, 10.</note> as the thinges that are in Earth. Summarily, the Apoſtle there, as in other ſundry places teacheth, that whatſoeuer good thinges we haue receiued, or are to receiue from the firſt to the laſt, from our eternall Election, to our future Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; wee haue, and ſhall haue them one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Chriſt, and by Chriſt; in whom wee hold them all in <hi>Capite</hi> from him: Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer therefore are choſen of God to life euerlaſting, beſide that they are choſen in Chriſt, they are Predeſtinated vnto Chriſt; that is, to the vnion and communion of Chriſt: ſo that by him it is of neceſsitie, we attaine all other thinges.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond Benefite of God, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of our Election, is our effectuall Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Chriſt and his Goſpell; by which the Elect onely are called, becauſe it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>According to his owne purpoſe &amp; grace, which is giuen to vs in Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The outward calling is common with the reſt, with the verie Rebrobates, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this Aphoriſme of our Sauiour, <hi>Many are called,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.47.</note> 
               <hi>But few are choſen.</hi> But the inward true calling, by which the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is enlightned, with the ſauing knowledge of God, &amp; the will is inclined to the will of God, is the peculiar of the part predeſtinate. This vocation effectuall
<pb facs="tcp:16347:33"/> is diſcerned, by the verie effects thereof: Whereof two are immediate. 1. The hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hearing of Gods word, togeather with the vnderſtanding therof, coupled, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted, with conſtancie, &amp; cheerefulneſſe. 2. A ſerious and ſure fayth, &amp; affiance that we haue in the ſame. Hence is it,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.47.</note> that is ſaide by our Sauiour: <hi>Hee that is of God,</hi> (that is to meane by election, and effectuall vacation) <hi>heareth Gods word:</hi> (that is, willingly, cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and continually.) <hi>Yee therefore heare it not, becauſe ye are not of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This vocation of ours, is done not onely by the preaching of the worde, (albeit that is the ordinarie meanes wherewith God effecteth it,) but ſometimes he vſeth other helpes, as Prayer, the conſideration of his Miracles, the admonition of Friendes, the interpoſition of afflictions, the inward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of his Spirit. <hi>Juſtinus Martyr,</hi> (as witneſſeth <hi>Euſebius</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. Lib. 4. &amp;. 8.</note>) was won to the ſayth by the regard he had to the rage of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants,<note place="margin">Aug. Confeſſ. Lib. 3. Cap. 4.</note> and to the patient ſuffrings of the Saintes. <hi>Augustine</hi> in his Confeſſions tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, that hee was conuerted to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſme, by reading an heathniſh Booke of <hi>Cicero,</hi> indorced &amp; ſuperſcribed <hi>Hertenſius,</hi> the forme of his confeſſion is thus, <hi>Jlle Liber mutauit affectum meum, et ad teipſum Domine mutanit preces meas:</hi> That Booke turned my
<pb facs="tcp:16347:34"/> minde, and turned my Prayers vnto thee O Lord my God. God in mollifying our Heartes,<note place="margin">Or any other thing of that nature.</note> and conuerting vs, doth as hee that would ſoften the Waxe that is hard, to make it apt to take an impreſsion: Firſt he chafeth it vp and downe betweene his handes, he oyleth it, he dippeth it in warme Water, he ſetteth it againſt the Fire, and then bringeth it to the Stampe or Preſſe: and if none of theſe will doe it good, then he medleth no more with it, but as a thing vnprofitable, hee doth vtterly reiect it. This is the courſe that God taketh in the mollifying and ſoftning of our heartes. Firſt he taketh vs as it were into his hands, rubbing and ſtroaking vs with the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of his Benefites, then he ſuppleth vs with his holy Inſpirations, the vnction and comfortable oyle of his Grace. 3. Hee waſheth and rinſeth vs with the Waters of his Pleaſures as out of a Riuer. 4. And ſometimes worketh our compunction by the fierie tryall of Perſecution. 5. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſtriketh vs out of life with the hammer of Death. If none of theſe callinges will make vs come to him, hee then caſteth all ſuch ſinners into Hell; as all the people that forget God, and will not obey his heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Calling: Where Fire and Brimſtone, Storme and Tempeſt, ſhall be their portion
<pb facs="tcp:16347:34"/> to drinke. He calleth by his Word, ſuch as are of age: wherfore it is ſaid to the Church of <hi>Laodicea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Behold, I ſtand at the doore and knocke, if any man ſhall heare my voyce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and open the doore, I will come in to him, and ſuppe with him, and hee with mee:</hi> wherfore Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If any man loueth me, and keepeth my wordes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.</note> 
               <hi>my Father ſhall loue him, and we will come and abide with him.</hi> But withal, he chiefly worketh our Vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by his inward inſpiration, by the which the Father draweth by the Spirit, them that come to Chriſt, the Dignation and Grace which he giueth to Infantes. Which Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is the introduction into our ſtate of ſaluation in this preſent life. Wherfore vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Apoſtles in the frontiſpire &amp; fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of their letters to the Churches ſpeake of this Vocation,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.7.8. 1. Cor. 1.2.</note> inſcribing and entitling them, <hi>Saintes by calling.</hi> Therefore it muſt needes be, that whoſoeuer be Elected in Chriſt, be (at their appoynted time) effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called, and drawne vnto him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third benefite of God, and effect and proofe of our Predeſtination, proper onely to the Elect, is <hi>Fayth;</hi> without which,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> in the teſtimonie of the Apoſtle, it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to pleaſe God: For by this, we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated into Chriſt, we are made mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his body: without which Fayth,
<pb facs="tcp:16347:35"/> no fleſh can be ſaued. In Infantos the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Fayth, (which is a knowledge of Chriſt and confidence in him) is not, as not capable thereof, in reſpect of their age; but they haue notwithſtanding, the Spirit and life of Fayth, which in proceſſe of time will breake foorth, as thoſe Scripture p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces prooue, which teach, That Saluation commeth to all by Fayth; and how that without Fayth, it is altogeather impoſsible for any to pleaſe God. That this is the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and fruite of Election, the Apoſtle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiciouſly and openly deliuereth,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.25.</note> where he witneſſeth of himſelfe, that hee obtained mercie of the Lord (that is, in his ſacred and ſecret decree of Predeſtination) to be fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Wherefore, whoſoeuer are Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated to eternall life in Chriſt, they are elected to this Fayth, the effect thereof; and therefore perforce they muſt at laſt beleeue in Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth benefite, and effect is <hi>Juſtification,</hi> that is, the free remiſsion of our ſinnes, and the imputation of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of Chriſt. So that the forme of Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, is as it were a kind of tranſlation of our ſinnes to Chriſt, and of Chriſts righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to vs, by reaſon of this diuine imputation. It is ſtiled, <hi>The Righteouſneſse of Christ,</hi> becauſe it is out of vs, and it is in the humanitie of Chriſt, as in the ſubiect. This
<pb facs="tcp:16347:35"/> naturally followeth Fayth at the heeles, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as thoſe that are endowed with this Fayth, are therewithall alſo Iuſtified. That this Iuſtification is an effect of Election,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note> the Apoſtle inſinuateth by ſetting it vpon the head of our Vocation, adioyned to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination immediatly before. Now this is not effected in vs while wee are in this world, but in the Pardon of our ſinnes, and in the imputation of his perfect obedience to vs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The fift benefit and effect, is <hi>Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> and <hi>Sanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fication</hi> by the Spirit, while we become <hi>New creatures</hi> by him, and ſo the Sonnes of God not onely by Adoption, but by regeneration alſo. For Chriſt when he Iuſtifieth vs, he not onely remitteth our vnrighteouſneſſe, and imputeth his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto vs: but alſo taketh away our heart of Stone, &amp; giueth vs his owne heart of Fleſh vnto vs; putteth off our Old man, and cloatheth vs with his New one, and ſtrippeth vs of our inward corruption, and maketh vs pertakers of his owne Nature: and ſo indeed, of the Sonnes of Men, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs the Sonnes of God, and Brethren vnto him. Wherefore wee are ſayd to be Predeſtinated by Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.5. Ioh. 8.6.</note> 
               <hi>That wee ſhould be holy, and without blame befo e him.</hi> And hence is this ſaying of our Sauiour, <hi>That which is borne of the Spirit, is Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb facs="tcp:16347:36"/>6. From this roote ſpringeth the ſixth Branch of our Election, which is, The loue of Righteouſneſſe, and hatred of Sinne: For in Regeneration, there is, <hi>To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rs a quo, et termanus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> An auerſion from ſinne, and a conuerſion to God: the morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the old <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>am,</hi> and the viuifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the New: the alteration of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Nature corrupted, into the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Diuine nature, by the Holy ghoſt ſanctified: which is noted in their Walke, of which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Rom. 8 1.</note> which is, <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter the fleſh, but after the ſpirit:</hi> And in the diſtaſte, their Stomackes take of carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 paragraph">
                     <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>They ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ur not the th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Fleſh, but of the ſpirit.</hi> Now the firſt affectes of the Fleſh, are <hi>Loue of ſinne,</hi> which is the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the fl ſh:</hi> and ſo on the contrarie ſide, <hi>The hatred of Righteouſneſſe, and of the Law of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which are not of the Father, but of the World: For that which properly is ſpoken of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5 8.</note> 
               <hi>Thou hast loued Righteouſneſse, and hated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>quitie,</hi> is not improperly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of all that are the members of Chriſt; wherefore <hi>Dauid,</hi> who beareth the perſon of all the Elect, and expreſſeth their diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3.</note> ſaith of himſelfe; <hi>J haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oued thy Law. Thy L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> within my heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 paragraph">
                     <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>J hate all theſe that are workers of iniquitie. J will not ſit among the Wicked.</hi> Such affections <hi>S. Paul</hi> deliuereth vs. <hi>J delight in the Law of God concerning the
<pb facs="tcp:16347:36"/> Inner man,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.23.</note> as I haue an inward and a better birth.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Now theſe two Affections, the firſt fruites of Regeneration, beget the ſeuenth Effect, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> endea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our to doe Good workes;</hi> that is, to forſake Sinne, and to fulfill the Law. For hee that hateth any thing from his heart, hee ſhunneth and auoydeth it all that he may. And ſo of the other ſide, hee that inwardly loueth a thing, hee purſueth it with the hotteſt contention that can be. This diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theirs in theſe two oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions, the Apoſtle thus ſpeaketh of: <hi>He that doth righteouſnes, is righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>as he is righteous. Hee that committeth ſinne, is of the Devill: For the Deuill ſinneth from the beginning.</hi> Now Chriſt came into the World, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue the workes of the Deuill in the Elect; But in the Reprobate, he ſuffereth them to remaine ſtill as they are; becauſe he was neuer ſtated in them, they were not giuen him of his Father, to be purged, regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſaued. Wherefore Chriſt being preor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinated to performe all theſe workes, and no good thing is done in vs, which was not in Chriſt prepared for vs from all eternitie: it is more then manifeſt that our ſollicitude of good works, is the effect of our Election. This the Apoſtle ſheweth plainely, where he ſayth;<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Wee are cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted in Chriſt Ieſus vnto go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which God hath ordained that wee
<pb facs="tcp:16347:37"/> ſhould walke in them.</hi> This duetie as more then neceſſarie, is commended and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs by Saint <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.10.</note> in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept hee preſcribeth vs, <hi>Giue diligence to make your Calling and Election ſure;</hi> that is, by Good workes: as many coppies haue it. For to whom ſhould we make it ſure? Not to God: for it was ſure to him before all worldes; but to our ſelues, and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Now becauſe while we ſeeke the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, and are carefull of Good works, and we refuſe to faſhion our ſelues accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this world in the luſtes and ſinnes thereof, the Fleſh, the World and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, combine and hange togeather like the Skales of <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> and diſplay their Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Hoſtilitie againſt vs: whereby through the malice that is in their heartes, and the might that is in their handes, they often get the vpper hand of vs; or if they winne vs not, at the leaſt they wearie vs: and therefore are inforced to flee vnto God as to our Citie of refuge. Heere com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in the eight effect of Predeſtination; <hi>Jnuocation on the name of God,</hi> that by his right hand, and holy arme, wee may haue the victorie. For this is the propertie of the Spirit which the Elect haue, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke them to pray:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.16.</note> 
               <hi>Wee know not how to pray: but the ſpirit it ſelfe maketh request for vs with
<pb facs="tcp:16347:37"/> ſighes which cannot be expreſsed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>And becauſe wee are Sonnes, God hath ſent foorth the Spirit of his Sonne into your heartes, which cryeth Abba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> 
               <hi>Father.</hi> It is the will of God wee ſhould <hi>Call vpon him in the time of trouble,</hi> and he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to heare vs.</p>
            <p n="9">9. From theſe premiſſes, proceedeth the ninth propertie of Predeſtination, which is, <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ence,</hi> and perpetuall compunction for our dayly and deadly ſinnes; an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weariſome wiſh of proceeding in Pietie: ſo as in this reſpect onely, wee deſire our diſſolution, to be with Chriſt; that the end of our life, might make an end of the life of ſinne. That this is incident to all the Elect, the Apoſtle thus ſpeaking in the name of all the Elect, vnto vs, thus witneſſeth: <hi>O wretched man that J am,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.24. Phil. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall deliuer mee from the body of this death?</hi> As in this wiſh that elſe where he maketh: <hi>I deſire to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, and to be with Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. This nynth, is the breeder of this tenth effect, which is a ſeruent affection to Chriſts ſecond comming, to ſet an ende to our ſorrowes and ſinnes, and to perfect and conſummate his Kingdome: That this is the Godly minde of the Elect, Saint <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a l</hi> teacheth vs, where hee telleth vs of them:<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>That they loue his glorious comming.</hi> This is the <hi>Reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bilis Eccho,</hi> that Saint <hi>John</hi> giueth,<note place="margin">Apo. 22.17 20.</note> anſwere the voice of the Bride-groome,
<pb facs="tcp:16347:38"/> and Spouſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>Euen ſo come Lord Jeſus.</hi> It is the poynt of Prayer Chriſt teacheth vs, in his preſcribed coppie of Prayer:<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> 
               <hi>Thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. Now becauſe ſuch as pray thus vnto God, are alſo heard according to his word of promiſe vnto them:<note place="margin">Rom. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt call vpon me in the time of trouble, and I will heare thee.</hi> Hence is it manifeſt, that the eleuenth ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of predeſtination, is our Comfort, and Ioy that wee haue in tribulations; thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> 
               <hi>Wee reioyce in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations: Knowing that tribulation bringeth forth patience.</hi> And ſo a recouerie of our ſelues, and a new life: So that it falleth out to the beſt, come what can come to thoſe that are E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: For the Elect, albeit they yeeld ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the playne field, in their Spirituall ſkirmiſh, yet becauſe by and by they haue helpe from Heauen of Chriſt, they ariſe with great Spirits, and they runne the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle againſt Sinne, and Sathan, and all the vnited troopes of Temptations, of Hoſtile affections; continuing the Warres, till they haue wonne the Fielde, as certaine in themſelues of the Conqueſt, and the Crowne.</p>
            <p n="12">12. This certaintie is the twelfe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of our predeſtination to all felicitie, common to all the companie of the Elect: this is the conſequent and concluſion of
<pb facs="tcp:16347:38"/> the Apoſtle <hi>What ſhall wee ſay to theſe things?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 24.24.</note> 
               <hi>Jf God be on our ſide, who can be against vs?</hi> And hence is it, that the Lord Ieſus giueth vs this comfort; that not by the comming of Antichriſt himſelfe, and all his illuſions, the Elect can be illuded.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Now from hence breaketh out the laſt benefite of God, &amp; effect of our Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is, <hi>Perſeuerance in the Fayth,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of Chriſt, conſorted with a minde to an holy life, and a deſire to ſet out Gods glorie. This gift goeth in common among all the Elect, according to promiſe in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie by <hi>Jeremie, I will giue my feare into theyr heartes, that they depart not from mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now if the teſtimonie of Gods ſpirit hath not ſuch ſtrength and vertue in the Elect, as to ſecure them in this caſe; then may they iudge of their Election, by that other effect of the Holy ghoſt in our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, namely, Sanctification; as wee vſe to iudge by Heate, that there is Fire, when we can not ſee the Flame it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Our Spirit performeth teſtimonie two wayes to our certaine Election. 1. By in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Tokens in it ſelfe. 2. By outward Fruites. The inward Tokens are of two ſortes. 1. Such as reſpect our Sinnes. 2. Such as reſpect the Mercie of God in Chriſt. The firſt are in reſpect of ſinnes paſt, preſent, or to come. The ſigne in the
<pb facs="tcp:16347:39"/> Spirit which concerneth ſinnes paſt, is godly ſorrow; which is a pricking in the heart, cauſed by an inward feeling of Gods wrath, and of damnation that enſueth, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned and diſtinguiſhed from a ſecular ſorrow, by theſe ſymptomes and ſignes. 1. A care to leaue our ſinnes. 2. An accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation that we take out with our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. 3. A griefe and vexation that we are in for them. 4. A feare of our future relapſe into them. 5. A deſire of Gods ſtrength &amp; aſsiſtance againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 6 Zeale to all ſeruices of pietie, contrarie to all our former iniquities. 7. A godly reuenge we take of our bodies, in ſubduing them to the ſpirit: This ſorrow is in ſome more, in ſome leſſe; God out of his wiſedome laying out to euery one his portion, beſt fitting with his condition, and ſufficient to ſaluation, in the leaſt proportion; as a Pinne or Needle ſerueth ſometimes to let out the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a running ſoare, aſwell as a Knife and Launcer.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Token which is in regard of ſinnes preſent is the combate betweene the Fleſh and the Spirit, proper to them that are regenerate, who are partly Fleſh and partly Spirit. Betweene theſe two enemies, there is no equalitie, but the Fleſh ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure exceedeth the Spirit. The Fleſh reſembling vaſt <hi>Goliah,</hi> and the Spirit
<pb facs="tcp:16347:39"/> litle <hi>Dauid.</hi> I compare the Spirit to litle <hi>Dauid,</hi> becauſe the meaſure is but litle that we haue in this life:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.23.</note> For heere wee receiue but the Firſt fruites of the Spirit. Wee may not looke for the fulneſſe thereof before the life to come yet the efficacie and power of the Spirit is ſo great, as it may ordinarily preuaile againſt the Fleſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For the Fleſh receiueth her deadly wound ſodainely, in the very nicke and moment of our conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and euer after languiſheth and pineth away; and therefore it fighteth but as a maymed Souldier: and the Spirit is conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually ſtrengthned and confirmed by the Spirit of God. And it is <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il</hi> and <hi>Iouial,</hi> and the vertue thereof is like Muske, one graine whereof is more fragrant and redo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, then many ounces of other Spices and Confections.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Token that reſpect ſinne to come<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is a care to preuent it: Saint <hi>John</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this marke of Gods Children, where he ſayeth, <hi>He that is borne of God, ſinneth not;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t keepeth himſelfe, that the wicked one touch him not.</hi> And this care extendeth it ſelfe, not onely to the well diſpoſing of the outward actions, but alſo to the good rule of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thoughtes of the heart: For where the word of God worketh, there,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.5.</note> 
               <hi>Euery thought is brought into captiuitie, to the obedience of Chriſt:</hi> And there, the Apoſtles direction
<pb facs="tcp:16347:40"/> is followed:<note place="margin">Phil. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoeuer things are true, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer things are honeſt, &amp;c. thinke on the e things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Tokens which concerne Gods mercie, are chiefely two. 1. When a Man feeles himſelfe diſtreſſed with the Burthen of his Sinnes, or when he apprehendes the heauie diſpleaſure of God in his Soule, for them: And further, feeleth the neede he hath of Chriſt and therewith, gaſpeth for the recouerie of Gods fauour, in the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſt, and that aboue all other thinges in the world: To all ſuch, are moſt cordiall promiſes made, which can haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to none but to the Elect, as where Chriſt ſayeth: <hi>If any man th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, let him come to me and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 7.37.</note> 
               <hi>He that bel eueth in me, (as ſayeth the Scriptures) out of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elly ſhall flow Riuers of Water of life.</hi> As where the Spirit ſayeth: <hi>I will giue to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is a thirſt, of the Well of the Water of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e freely.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 21.6.</note> Now if hee that thirſteth drinke of theſe Waters, marke what followeth: <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſoeuer drinketh of the VVate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that I ſhall giue him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall neuer b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more a thirst: But the VVater that I ſhall g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue him, ſhall be, in time, a VVell of VVater ſpringing vp vnto euerlasting life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond is a ſtrange affection wrought in the heart by the Spirit of God, whereby a Man doth ſo rate the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt, as all other thinges vnder the Roofe of Heauen, are deemed but as
<pb facs="tcp:16347:40"/> Doung in compariſon thereof: This minde was <hi>Paul</hi> in, where hee ſayeth: <hi>I account all thinges but Doung, to gaine Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil 3.8.</note> And this affection, the Parable in the Ghoſpell poynteth at,<note place="margin">Math. 13.44.</note> vnder the ſimilitude of the concealed Treaſure, &amp; the peereles Pearle for which the Euangelicall Merchant ſold away his temporalles.</p>
            <p>Now euery one ſaigneth himſelfe to be of this affection, and that he more eſteemeth a droppe of Chriſtes blood, then all the Kingdomes of the world: when as the euent ſheweth the contrarie, that this is but the ſmooth voyce of <hi>Jacob,</hi> they are ſpaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the rough and hairie generation of <hi>Eſau;</hi> more greedie of his brother <hi>Iacobs</hi> red Broth, then of his Father <hi>Iſackes</hi> Bleſsing: Of the brood of the old <hi>Jſraelites,</hi> that more regarded their rancker and groſſer diets, their Onions, Garlicke, Leekes, and ſuch pelfe, &amp; the Fleſh-pots of <hi>Aegipt;</hi> then the riches of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>naan,</hi> the Land of Promiſe. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> all the ſort of them, more ſetting by their Swine, then by their Sauiour. Now to vnmaske ſuch a diſguiſed Hipocrite, there be two proper markes to diſcerne this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from the falſe. 1. The firſt is his loue to a Chriſtian, in that regard onely that hee is a Chriſtian: for hee can not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme of Chriſt as he ought, that doth not in like ſort eſteeme of Chriſtes members.
<pb facs="tcp:16347:41"/> This is the Obſeruation giuen vs by our Sauiour, where he ſayth: <hi>He that receiueth a Prophet in the name of a Prophet, ſhall receiue a Prophets reward:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 10.41.</note> 
               <hi>and he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth a righteous man in the name of a righteous man, ſhall receiue the reward of a righteous man.</hi> And it is the ſigne S. <hi>John</hi> telleth vs of, where he ſayth; <hi>Hereby wee know that we are tranſlated from death to life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe wee loue the Brethren:</hi> that is, ſuch as are members, becauſe they are ſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond marke is, their loue to the ſecond comming of Chriſt either particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by death, or vniuerſally by the latter Iudgement, to no other end, but to haue a full fruition of Chriſt, S. <hi>Paul</hi> maketh this a marke of our adoption, where he ſayth; <hi>The Crowne of righteouſneſſe is laide vp for all them that loue the appearing of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note>The outward Token of our Adoption, is our New Obedience, and conformitie to Gods Law in an holy conuerſation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by Saint <hi>John,</hi> where he ſayeth: <hi>Hereby we are ſure that we know him, if we keepe his commandementes.</hi> Now we meane not ſuch exact &amp; abſolute obedience,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 23.</note> as the morall Law in the rigour thereof, looketh for at our handes; for then it ſhould not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token grace, but be the meanes of our dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation:
<pb facs="tcp:16347:41"/> But ſuch obedience as in the fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable acceptation of God, meaſuring a deede rather by the diſpoſition of the doer, then by the perfection of it; goeth for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant pay: Yet that we may not paye him Copper for good Coyne, this obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence muſt be thus qualified. Firſt, it muſt not come with paring Kniues to the Law of God, and cutte off and keepe ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements as they pleaſe, and keepe a part behinde with <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amas,</hi> and <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a,</hi> and diuide his worſhip, as the wrong Mother that pleaded before <hi>Salomo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> would haue the Childe deuided: Hee will haue our obedience to them all, or elſe to none of them all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> could heare <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> willingly, and did reforme many thinges by his meanes: And <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udas</hi> had many good partes in him, as heereby appeareth, that he was content to leaue all, and to follow Chriſt, and preached the Ghoſpell of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in <hi>Jurie,</hi> aſwell as the reſt: Yet all this was to no purpoſe, for that the one would not obey the ſeuenth Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in leauing his Brother <hi>Phi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ips</hi> Wife; and the other would not leaue his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe to dye for it. Entire and true o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, doth ſtretch out it ſelfe to all the Commandementes, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth, <hi>I ſhall not be confounded,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.6.</note> 
               <hi>when I haue reſpect to all thy
<pb facs="tcp:16347:42"/> Commandementes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 2.10.</note> Saint <hi>James</hi> condemneth him as guiltie of all, that is guiltie of one: That is, our obedience to many Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, is before God no obedience, but a flatte ſinne, if wittingly and willingly we leaue any one vndone. Hee that doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent himſelfe of one ſinne truely, doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of all: and hee tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> liue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but in one knowne ſinne, without repentance, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he pretend, indeed repentes of no ſinne.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, this Obedience muſt dilate it ſelfe to the whole courſe of our life, after our conuerſion and repentance: for we are not to iudge of a man by one or two good deedes; but by the carriage of himſelfe in the whole courſe of his life. A man is, as his life is: They are not the ſlippes and ſalles that he hath by weakneſſe of nature, that can preiudice his Election, ſo he renueth his repentance for his new treſpaſſes, &amp; dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not in ſinne in a ſenſeleſſe ſecuritie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly and laſtly, this Obedience, muſt be from the whole man, as Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the cauſe thereof,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 3.13.</note> is through the whole man in Body, Soule, and Spirit. Alſo, Obedience is the fruite of Loue; and Loue is from a pure Heart, a good Conſcience, and Fayth vnfained.</p>
            <p>Thus wee teach not that men muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the forgiueneſſe of their ſinnes, while
<pb facs="tcp:16347:42"/> they lie, and liue in them, for that were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togeather to teach falſehood for trueth. Hee that beleeues the Pardon of his ſinnes by true Fayth, hath the ſpirit of God in him, and a conſtant purpoſe not to ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, If hee doe, it is againſt his minde; it is not hee that doth it, but the ſinne that dwelleth in him, and his caſe ſtandeth thus. He hath by his ſinne giuen a blow to his Conſcience, weakned his Fayth, bereaued himſelfe of the Fauour of God as much as in him is, made himſelfe guiltie of ſinne, and worthy of damnation. And God for his part, accordingly turnes the wonted ſignes of his Fauour, into ſignes of Anger and Diſpleaſure; and though it be pardoned in the purpoſe of God, yet is it not actually pardoned, till the partie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</p>
            <p>Wherefore heere is Anſwere to this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, How a man may be aſſured of his Adoption, if he want the Teſtimonie from Heauen, which is the Spirit of God. For as Fire is knowne by two properties, of the heate, of the Flame: Wee may know it to be Fire ſtill, by the verie heate, though it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth no Flame, So if a man hath not the Witneſſe of Gods Spirit, by the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of our Spirit, our ſanctification; wee haue certificate not obſcure of our Electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>If it ſhall further grow into queſtion,
<pb facs="tcp:16347:43"/> How it is that after all our curious Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, we finde but few ſignes of Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in our ſelues? In this caſe they muſt haue recourſe to the leaſt meaſure of Grace, which being but of the ſize of a Graine of Muſtardſeed, and but of the ſtrength of a weake Infant, it is ſufficient to engraffe them into Chriſt; and therefore they muſt not doubt of their Election becauſe they find their Fayth feeble, and the effectes of the Holy ghoſt faint within them: which I ſpeake not to the end to lead men into ſecuritie, &amp; that they ſhould content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with theſe ſmall beginninges of Grace, but onely to ſhew how any may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure themſelues that they are at the leaſt, Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es in Chriſt; adding this withall, that they which haue no more but theſe ſmall beginninges, muſt be carefull to increaſe them, <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta non progre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i eſt regredi,</hi> Not to goe forward, is to goe backward.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, and what if the Chriſtian ſoule as yet hath not found this litle meaſure of Grace and hath no meanes in the world of aſſuraunce? Hee muſt not deſpaire, but perſwade himſelfe in this, that though hee wantes aſſuraunce now, yet hee may haue the ſame hereafter.</p>
            <p>No man may peremptorily conclude, and ſet downe, that himſelfe, or any other is a Reprobate: For Gods wayes are not as
<pb facs="tcp:16347:43"/> mans wayes, but h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e preferres ſuch, often times as ſeeme greateſt ſtrangers and ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antes vnto him vnto his Kingdome, when he caſteth out thoſe whom the world eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Children of the Kingdome. So ſayth our Sauiour:<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th. 21.31.</note> 
               <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cans and Harlots goe before you.</hi> And the Parable telleth vs, how, <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y an one is called at the eleuenth houre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 20.6.</note> as it appeareth by the example of the remor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Theefe vpon the Croſſe. But in the meane while be we perſwaded, to heare the Word of God, and to receiue the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: For by our care in comming to the Lords Vineyard, and conuerſing about the Wine-preſſe, we ſhall finde that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Wine of Gods Grace, as ſhall ſerue to make glad the heart of man. When ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and death aſſaulteth vs, the very choſen of God muſt prepare themſelues to temptations, the Deuill then beſtirring him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe all he may, and ſitting our ſoules to the courſeſt branne, as curiouſly as euer <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an</hi> did ranſacke <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſtuffe: And few there be that can iudge of theſe terrors of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, but ſuch an one as can ſay, <hi>Quarum pars magnafi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Now when men lay thus in darkneſſe and in the region and ſhadow of death, vnleſſe God ſhould from Heauen with a gracious aſpect, looke vpon them in the face of his Annoynted, and ſtreame downe vnto them in this life, ſome light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb facs="tcp:16347:44"/> beames of his loue in Chriſt, by the operation of his holy Spirit, it would be very hard with the beſt of them all.</p>
            <p>Finally, as euery one of the Elect, in this life, is made certaine of his Election, aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained thereof by the meanes aboue men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned: ſo a due time by God is determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the ſame, tearmed in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor 6.2. Luk. 19.42.</note> 
               <hi>The Acceptable time: the day of Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The time of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitation:</hi> Before which time of our bleſſed Vocation, we neuer are perſwaded, or once thinke of our Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: as wee ſee in the examples of <hi>Mathew,</hi> wholly betaking himſelfe to his Toll-houſe: as in <hi>Paul,</hi> before his conuerſion, when he was a <hi>Saul,</hi> and vexed the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation: and in many ſuch.</p>
            <p>Againe, many after the time of their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, are not by and by made certaine of their Election: but to ſome ſooner, to ſome later, is this Grace afforded.</p>
            <p>A Chriſtian ſoule often ſeeketh after this comfort in his Bedde by Prayers, and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it not; as the Spouſe the Church did her Bridegroome in the 3. of the <hi>Canticles, In my Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de by night,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cantic. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>J ſought him that my ſoule I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nea; J ſought him, but I found him not.</hi> Hee intreateth the counſaile and comfort of his friendes, and the helpe of their holy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;<note place="margin">verſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and yet found him not: The complaint the Spouſe maketh in the ſame place. Hee
<pb facs="tcp:16347:44"/> reſorteth to the Godly Preachers of the word, and yet ſpeedeth not:<note place="margin">verſ. 3.</note> which was ſtill the ſaid Churches caſe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, when all helpe and hepes fayled her, the Bridegrome came,<note place="margin">verſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Adiutor in oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bus,</hi> An helper in the needfull time of trouble: he came on his owne accord, as he hath ſo done to diuerſe in the like caſe. 1. Then Fayth taketh vp as it were a new life, groweth into heart, &amp; taketh hold on Chriſt. 2. Then hath the Soule very nigh ſocietie, and coniunction with GOD.<note place="margin">verſ. 5.</note> 3. Then commeth ioy in the Holy ghoſt, and peace of Conſcience, as a ſweete ſleepe commeth on a weariſome body,<note place="margin">verſ. 6.</note> and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth all the partes of the body with his refreſhing deawe. 4. Then is the Heart lifted vp to Heauen with holy thoughtes,<note place="margin">verſ. 8.9.10.</note> and Prayers, which mount vpward as Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of Smoake, pleaſant as perfumed with Myrrhe and Incenſe. 5. Then is it raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and out of it ſelfe, in the muze and meditation of his glorious condition in the Heauenly kingdome. 6. Then it endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoreth to perſwade others to conſider of the Glorie of Chriſt, and of his Kingdome.<note place="margin">verſ. 11.</note> 7. After all theſe,<note place="margin">Chap. 4. verſ. 1. to the cha. 15.</note> Chriſt reuealeth to his Seruant, the happineſſe of his eſtate in this life, and the other more plainely &amp; openly then euer he did before;<note place="margin">verſ. 16.</note> and giueth him a ſight of ſuch Graces and Benefites, as hee
<pb facs="tcp:16347:45"/> hath beſtowed on him. 8. The Chriſtian preſenteth his Prayers to Chriſt, that hee would breath and blow vpon him with his Spirit, that ſo hee might bring foorth ſuch fruites as he hath, of thankfulneſſe to the Lord. Laſtly, Chriſt yeeldeth to all we pray for, and giueth vs our heartes deſire; and doth not denie vs the requeſt of our lippes.</p>
            <p>Now for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, and all other his Graces and Bleſsinges beſtowed vpon vs; to him, with his bleſſed Sonne, and Holy ſpirit, three perſons, one eternall and euerliuing GOD, be aſcribed all Praiſe, Power, and Glorie, now and euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16347:45"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
